Foreword

I’m grateful to be asked to write a foreword to this well-written and well-named book, for I might otherwise not have had the rich and rewarding experience of reading it. So many books are published every year that it’s impossible to keep up with them all, but this is one I’d be very sorry to have missed.

When I started out in publishing, back when dinosaurs ruled the earth, about half the books we worked on were set in Linotype, and plenty of seasoned professionals were happy to assure me that it would be with us forever, phototypesetting being just another flash in the pan. Well, hot metal has been history for some time now, and mainframe-based composition joined it awhile back too, for that matter, yet here we are, still making books—Marshall McLuhan notwithstanding. Five and a half centuries of the printed book have brought more changes to the methods and tools and techniques than anyone outside the book business could possibly imagine, but the process of making books remains remarkably the same. Writing, editing, designing, setting, proofreading, correcting, printing, distributing, and—for some books at least—indexing.

Most of us in the industry do our job as well as we can, day in, day out, but a small minority take the trouble to write down what they’ve learned for the benefit of the rest of us. Of course, their works get dated as new ways of doing things come along, but the best ones still have a lot to say even after time goes by. To name the first examples that come to mind, there are Marshal Lee’s Bookmaking: Editing, Design, Production, Jason Epstein’s Book Business: Publishing Past, Present, and Future, Rich Hendel’s On Book Design, Alexander Lawson’s Anatomy of a Typeface, Herbert Bailey’s The Art and Science of Book Publishing, and as you’re reading this, you are probably wondering why I left your own favorites off the list. For my money, this book is another candidate for consideration for your working bookshelf, somewhere near Chicago and Words into Type.

As its title makes clear, this book is intended for editors and authors, but I suspect many indexers will learn quite a bit from it as well. I don’t think I’ve ever picked up a work on design or editing without learning something from it, and we all have gaps in our knowledge of the field. In the compass of 100+ pages, Fred Leise, Kate Mertes, and Nan Badgett have laid out the essentials of indexing: the who, what, when, where, why, and how—and the how much, as well. Among many other things, I’m impressed by the deftness of the redundancy of the book. Just as an index has built-in redundancy in the form of cross-references to save the reader time and effort, so they have the occasional dash of repeated information, usually with just the proper twist, to make sure we get it and get it right: what an index is; what kinds there are; what makes a good one; how many there need to be; how the index should look and how long it should be; how to get an index made and what form it should take. All these topics and more are thoroughly, expertly, and even entertainingly covered, with plenty of specific examples and illustrations of every aspect of indexes you could expect, and probably a few more besides.

And if you think the subject is dry or mundane, this book will help you get over that notion in a hurry. For example, it probably wouldn’t occur to most people that fiction might be indexed. As this book makes clear, an index usually should not be written by the author of the book, but a great counterexample is Vladimir Nabokov’s index to Pale Fire. If you think you know what an index is—just an alphabetical list of topics, along with the pages where they’re mentioned—then consider the many different kinds of indexes: indexes of names, of places, of subjects; indexes of maps and atlases and directories. Consider, too, such things as the effect of the trim size of the book on the structure and format of the index or indexes. From the basic principles of indexing, such as the choice of alphabetizing system or how best to handle the subject of a book itself (the index’s “metasubject”), to the details of the types of software that indexers use to facilitate the work or how best to find the indexer you need for your specific project, the book is loaded with relevant information, as up to date as a constantly changing world will allow.

I could go on, but you get the point. Page for page, this book delivers, and after reading it for the first time, you’ll never think about indexes, indexing, or indexers quite the same way again. After all, indexing shares one thing in common with editing, design, typesetting, proofreading, printing, and so forth. It’s basically invisible to the reader, except when something goes wrong. Even more than these other functions, it seems to me that indexing resembles translation: If a reader thinks about it at all, he or she probably considers it one of those things that “just happens.” Or, worse yet, something that nowadays is probably computerized. If you’ve ever seen a totally computerized translation, you know that we aren’t quite ready to dispense with the human element. Similarly, an index probably should not contain an entry such as “Wittgenstein, Ludwig: 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, …”

Someone once said—and I’ll have you know that the Internet has been absolutely useless at helping me find out who it was—that we know so much more today about building materials and construction techniques than did the master masons who put up the great cathedrals, and that we understand so much less. After you’ve read this book, not only will you know more about indexes and books than you ever did, you’ll also understand a great deal more.

—Dan Kirklin

Dan Kirklin is a graduate of Indiana University and taught English and German at the secondary level for five years before becoming a proofreader-copyeditor at Bobbs-Merrill, and then an editor at Bobbs-Merrill Educational Publishing. He later worked as an editor, designer, indexer, programmer, and packager at Alexander Graphics Ltd., notably producing for Harper & Row The New Dictionary of American Slang and a revised edition of Benet’s Reader’s Encyclopedia, for which he wrote the data-processing program HARLOT (Harper And Row Lists Of Terms). Dan was managing editor at Hackett Publishing Company for 10 years and supervised production of nearly 200 titles, including the HPC edition of The Complete Works of Plato. Since 1998 he has been managing editor at Liberty Fund, a private educational foundation, which publishes more than 20 new and classic titles a year in history, economics, political theory, law, and other subjects.

About the Authors

Fred Leise

Prior to co-founding Intuitect (a software development company) in 2005, Fred Leise was an information architecture (IA) consultant, providing IA and taxonomy development services for such clients as Harpo, Inc., Abbott Laboratories, HP, Dow Corning, Accenture, the Social Security Administration, and Columbia College Chicago. Fred honed his IA skills as a member of the fabled Argus Associates in Ann Arbor, MI, where he worked under the direction of Lou Rosenfeld and Peter Morville.

He has worked as a freelance indexer since 1995, specializing in scholarly works in the humanities, including East Asian history and civilization, international relations, and politics. His index to Art and Affection: A Biography of Virginia Woolf by Panthea Reid was one of three works shortlisted for the 1998 ASI/H. W. Wilson Company Indexing Award. Fred indexed Mikhail Gorbachev’s My Country and the World in 2000.

Fred has written and spoken extensively on controlled vocabularies and indexing, in addition to presenting workshops on taxonomies and controlled vocabularies at the annual conferences of the Information Architecture Institute, the Special Libraries Association, and the American Society of Indexers (ASI). He has taught indexing for the University of Chicago Publishing Program, the Graduate School of Library and Information Science of Dominican University (River Forest, IL), and Columbia College Chicago. In September 2006, he was in Brunei and Kuala Lumpur presenting taxonomy workshops under the sponsorship of Singapore-based DZ Hampton. Fred is currently President-Elect of ASI, on whose board he has served two previous terms.

Kate Mertes

Kate Mertes is sole proprietor of Mertes Editorial Services, providing indexing, information retrieval, and editorial expertise for complex, challenging projects in law and the humanities. Kate has a BA in medieval studies, a PhD in medieval history, and a post-doctoral degree in theology. After teaching at university level for several years, she moved into publishing with a stint at Oxford English Dictionaries.

After nine years as a managing editor of indexing with Research Institute of America, a legal publishing company, Kate started her own business in 1998. She has lived in Alexandria, VA, since 1992.

Kate served on the board of ASI from 1998 to 2004, and was president of ASI in 2002 to 2003. She was president of the Washington, D.C., chapter of ASI from 2005 to 2006. Some of her recent projects include indexing the Oxford Jewish Study Bible, a 1,200-page edition of the works of James Wilson (a signatory of both the Declaration of Independence and the Constitution of 1787) for Liberty Fund, volumes in Cambridge University Press’s series on the history of Christianity, and legal texts for Thompson Publishing Group.

Kate is also the author of Good Governance and Politic Rule: The English Noble Household, 1250–1550, and has authored chapters in many of ASI’s publications on the indexing of legal, historical, and theological materials. She is currently composing a chapter on classical and medieval nomenclature for ASI’s new book on names and naming. Kate teaches a course on indexing for the Catholic University of America.

Nan Badgett

Nan Badgett, who does business as Word-a-bil-i-ty, has provided indexing and editorial services to publishers, corporate clients, and authors since 1991. Nan works almost exclusively on trade books, although she has authored indexes for textbooks, periodicals, and technical manuals. Her experience includes creating embedded indexes using both FrameMaker and Word. Areas of subject expertise include construction, home improvement, and woodworking; sports training and sports psychology; and sewing and crafts. She has worked in a variety of other subjects from education to bird watching. Nan has presented at ASI national conferences and has provided corporate training in indexing methods.

Prior to her indexing career, Nan worked as a legal assistant in a government agency, a corporate writer for a retail company, and a book production assistant for a book packager. She is also a published freelance writer. Nan has a BA in French and was trained in indexing through the USDA Graduate School. She was a founding member of the Arizona Chapter of ASI, and served that chapter as both president and secretary. Nan lives with her husband in Tucson, AZ, and is an avid cyclist and hiker.

Chapter 2

Numbers and Types of Indexes

This chapter looks at two basic issues associated with indexes. First, we look at the pros and cons of having more than one index associated with a specific text. Then we explore the various types of indexes, which come in more flavors than just a typical name/subject index.

NUMBERS OF INDEXES

Single vs. Multiple Indexes

The specific index or indexes used in any given context should be determined by the nature of the material being indexed, what users will be looking for, and the types of indexes that other similar publications provide. In general, it is preferable to use a single index to a document or document collection. As the NISO technical report on indexes (NISO-TR02-1997) notes: “Unified indexes should generally be preferred….” It goes on to say, however, that:

Separate indexes may also be desirable when it is awkward to assimilate verbal terms (using natural language words) with non-verbal terms, such as chemical formulae or patent numbers, or terms in different writing systems, such as the Roman alphabet and non-Roman scripts.

Clearly, separate indexes are merited when the principal of organization differs in two or more kinds of material. For example, geographic indexes are often classified by region, country, state, administrative district, city, and neighborhood, while a general subject index contains a single alphabetical list of main headings. An index to a car parts catalog would generally be ordered numerically by part number.

While multiple indexes have inherent difficulties (as we explain in the next section), there are a number of instances where multiple indexes are the norm. Legal volumes, for example, often contain a case and statute index that is separate from the subject index, where the flow of the subject index is not broken up or interrupted by long lists of names or statute numbers. News publications may have separate indexes for people and companies in addition to a subject index. According to Enid Zafran, a long-time indexer (private communication, June 23, 2007), major texts in the field of psychology traditionally have a separate scholar name index.

In cases where multiple indexes are used, it is important to clearly indicate to the reader that multiple indexes exist. Index headnotes should explain the scope of the index and refer readers to the additional indexes. Running heads may be used to specify the type of index, e.g., Name Index, rather than just the standard “Index” heading.

Problems with Multiple Indexes

When considering whether to use a single index or multiple indexes, editors should be aware that multiple indexes create significant usability problems. That is, users may not be aware of the other indexes available to them and may thus fail to find significant relevant information. If users are aware of the existence of multiple indexes, their information search becomes significantly less efficient, as they must now search in two or more places for relevant information.

In addition to the problem of finding and using multiple indexes, the use of explanatory inter-index cross-references may be necessary. For example, where a text uses separate author and subject indexes, the following pointers might be necessary:

Piaget, Jean

…

See also Piaget, Jean in author index

and

Piaget, Jean

…

See also Piaget, Jean in subject index

Such cross-references complicate users’ search, making them first look for the location of the other index, then search within that index to find another relevant entry. A much simpler solution would be a single index with both names and subjects:

Truman, Harry S.

…

administration of

…

TYPES OF INDEXES

Most of us are familiar with the standard back-of-book or journal index, one that combines access to people, places, things, and subjects/topics in a single alphabetical listing. However, there are many different types of indexes that can appear in publications, depending on the specific nature of the text being indexed.

In addition to basic subject indexes, some other possible index types include:

Geographic indexes
Name indexes
Legal case indexes (usually called table of cases)
Title indexes
Scientific name indexes
First-line indexes (for poetry)
Author indexes
Chemical indexes
Numerical indexes
Melodic indexes
Citation indexes

Each of these types of indexes will be discussed in detail.

Geographic Indexes

Usually appearing in conjunction with maps, atlases, or guidebooks, geographic indexes generally consist of an alphabetic list of geographic places. For maps or atlases, locators usually consist of map coordinates. For multistate or multination maps, entries are usually organized first by the largest geographic unit, moving through smaller units in turn. In the following example, taken from the Times Atlas of World History (London: Times Books Limited, 1979), locators refer to page/map number:

Aachen, 107/3, 212/1, 253/3

Aergau, 183/1

Aerhus, 101/2, 116/2

Abadan, 285/1

Abarshahr, 79/3

Abasgia, 113/1

This selection from the index to the 1993 edition of the Rand McNally Road Atlas also demonstrates the use of special typography (boldface) to differentiate counties from cities within the same index. A headnote (see Chapter 3) should be used to explain typeface meaning and locator construction.

Maryland

Aberdeen, B-15

Abingdon, C-15

Acokeek, G-12

Adelphi, D-7

Allegheny, B-5

Annapolis, C-14

Annapolis Jct., D-13

Ann Arundel, L-13

Note the use of grid identifiers, here row letter and column number, as locators.

Name Indexes

Separate name indexes are used only in those cases where adding the names into the subject index would significantly reduce its usability. The access mechanism to the 1,000-page London Encyclopedia (London: Macmillan London, 1983), for example, includes a “people” index, as well as a “general” index, which comprises streets, buildings, and other structures.

Name indexes are generally alphabetized by last name, then by first name:

Pallitser, A., 814

Palmer, E. W., 64

Palmer, Frederick, 673

Palmer, George, 342

Palmer, H., 30

Palmer, Sir Henry, 456

Palmer, James, 916

Palmer, John, 617

Titles or other honorifics are generally ignored when sorting names. Frequently the index drops titles, as they create complications as people get promoted to a higher military rank or otherwise change titles. Unless a client insists on titles, it is probably preferable to omit them.

Genealogical indexes, consisting of names only, often use last names as headings, with first names arranged under those as subheadings. The preceding name list, from the London Encyclopedia, would appear as follows in a genealogical index:

Pallitser

A., 814

Palmer

E. W., 64

Frederick, 673

George, 342

H., 30

Sir Henry, 456

James, 916

John, 617

Often, especially in historical texts or other material dealing with obscure individuals, only last names may be known. Or it may be that two individuals discussed in the text have the same name. In both cases it is usual to include a qualifier so that readers can properly identify each individual in the index.

Qualifiers may also be used, especially in indexes to biographies, so that readers can identify the relationship to the person who is the subject of the book. Two instances—name identification and name differentiation—appear in the following extract, headings taken from the index to The Life of an Unknown (New York: Columbia University Press, 2001). (Here, “P” refers to Louis-François Pinagot, the subject of the biography.)

Pinagot, Eugène (P’s son)

Pinagot, Evremont (P’s son)

Pinagot, Félice-Estelle (P’s granddaughter)

Pinagot, Françoise (P’s aunt)

Pinagot, Françoise (P’s daughter)

Pinagot, Héloise (daughter of P’s cousin Angelique)

Pinagot, Isaïe (daughter of P’s cousin Etienne)

Pinagot, Isaïe (P’s granddaughter)

Pinagot, Jacques (P’s father)

Pinagot, Jacques (P’s grandfather)

When necessary, birth/death dates or occupation may be used as distinguishing qualifiers.

Legal Case Indexes

Indexes to legal texts (also called tables of cases) present special problems. These are discussed in detail in another book published by the American Society of Indexers, Indexing Specialties: Law (Medford, NJ: Information Today, Inc., 2001). Only a brief overview is provided here.

In general, tables of cases should be used in legal texts or other documents that cover a significant number of legal cases. Standard form in legal case indexes for a main heading is A v. B, where A is the plaintiff and B the defendant. Case names may be italicized if they are included as part of a regular subject index.

When creating a table of cases, the indexer should enquire whether full citations are required, as they entail considerable work because of their length:

Bob’s Disc. Furniture, Inc. v. Bob’s Disc. Off-Price Superstores, Inc., 353 F. Supp. 2d 118 (D. Me. 2005)

or

Yassine, Inc. v. Bates Communication, Inc., 163 Ohio App. 3d 413, 2005 Ohio 5019, 837 N.E.2d 1272, 2005 Ohio App. LEXIS 4532 (Lucas County 2005), app. denied, 108 Ohio St. 3d 1474, 2006 Ohio 665, 842 N.E.2d 1053, 2006 Ohio LEXIS 460 (2006)

Alphabetization of legal indexes is first by plaintiff and then by defendant if necessary for disambiguation of otherwise identical entries.

The legal case index to Jay M. Feinman’s Law 101: Everything You Need to Know about the American Legal System includes these entries:

Raich v. Gonzalez

Rasul v. Bush

Regents of the University of California v. Bakke

Rhode Island v. Innis

Roe v. Wade

Romer v. Evans

Rosenberger v. Rector of the University of Virginia

Rylands v. Fletcher

In addition to a legal case index, a subject index will also be included in a legal text, providing access to specific legal concepts. Locators for legal texts may be page numbers or paragraph/section numbers if those are used throughout the text.

Title Indexes

It may be useful to add an index devoted solely to titles in texts that discuss a number of works of art (whether literature, music, or fine arts). To be most helpful to readers, title indexes should include the full title of the work of art, with cross-references from the work’s popular title or nickname. As with all works of art, standard practice dictates including the creator’s name as a qualifier.

La Gioconda. See Mona Lisa

…

Mona Lisa (La Gioconda, Leonardo da Vinci)

or

Pique dame. See The Queen of Spades

…

The Queen of Spades (Pique dame, Tchaikovsky)

Library catalogs often include access to information through a title index, in addition to author and subject indexes.

In especially large indexes, the indexer may prefer to divide information first by genre. The title index to a composer’s works, for example, might be categorized into chamber music, choral works, operas, orchestral works, and solo instrumental works. However, if the reader is unaware what category a specific work falls into, such a division may significantly hinder information finding. Careful consideration should be given as to whether to use genres as a way of organizing a title index.

Scientific Name Indexes

Especially in dense scientific texts, it may be helpful to the reader to create a separate index of scientific names. Scientific name indexes may consist entirely of scientific names for plants or animals or may contain common names as well. In the latter case it is useful to double-post entries under both the common and scientific names, with the alternate form of the term given as a qualifier (in parentheses).

In another arrangement, scientific and common names may both be separately indexed. This is the case, for example, with the index to Birds of North America, Revised and Updated: A Guide to Field Identification (New York: St. Martin’s Press, 2001).

In addition, where multiple species are discussed in a single text, it is customary to use the genus as the heading with the species as subheadings, as this excerpt from the Birds of North America demonstrates. Note that this same format is also used with common names:

Cormorant, Brandt’s

Double-crested

Great

Neotropic

Pelagic

Red-faced

Corvidae

Corvus brachyrhynchos

caurinus

corax

cryptoleucus

imparatus

ossifragus

Note here also the standard format for scientific names (Corvus brachyrhynchos), in which the genus is capitalized and the species given in lower case.

First-Line Indexes

First-line indexes are often found in collections of poetry. They allow readers to find a particular poem by means of the first line.

In the case of first-line indexes, alphabetization differs slightly from most indexes: Initial articles and prepositions are not ignored in determining alphabetical order. For example, the first-line index to the 1960 complete edition of Emily Dickinson poems (Thomas H. Johnson, ed., Boston: Little, Brown and Company) includes the following entries:

A bee his burnished carriage, 1339

A bird came down the walk, 328

A burdock clawed my gown, 229

A cup of lead across the sky, 1649

…

An honest tear, 1192

An hour is a sea, 825

…

Of bronze and blaze, 290

Of Brussels it was not, 602

Of consciousness her awful mate, 894

…

The fact that earth is heaven, 1408

The fairest home I ever knew, 1423

The farthest thunder that I heard, 1581

It should be noted that in this instance, the locators are not page numbers, but poem numbers. Also, this volume interestingly includes a subject index to the poems, which contains entries for “names mentioned in poems” and “places mentioned in poems.”

A first-line index is also useful in song collections, and such an index is often found in hymnals.

Indexes of first lines are generally flat lists, that is, there are no subheadings, as the first line of text is the identifying element in the index.

Author Indexes

Author indexes are regularly found in journals or article collections, volumes of essays, or any other text collection that brings together relatively short works of many different authors.

As in general name indexes, author indexes usually present the authors’ names in inverted order (last name first) and are alphabetized first by last name, then by first name or initial.

If necessary, qualifiers such as birth and death dates should be used to distinguish between authors of the same name.

Subheadings generally consist of the particular articles or essays that the author has written that are available in the collection being indexed. If the index is to multiple periodicals, the author index will also include the specific journal citation (i.e., volume, issue number, date, etc.) that an article appeared in, so as to enable proper retrieval.

Chemical Indexes

When the subject of an index is limited to or consists primarily of chemical names, it is customary to create a separate chemical index. In the case of a chemical index, all numerical and letter prefixes to the main chemical name, as well as internal numbers, are ignored in alphabetization except when needed for disambiguation of otherwise identical entries.

The following example taken from the Haz-Map Index of the National Institute of Medicine at the National Institutes of Health (hazmap.nlm.nih.gov/cgibin/hazmap_list?tbl=TblAgents&alpha=B) shows the typical arrangement of a chemical index:

Buclosamide

Bupirimate

1,3-Butadiene

n-Butane

1,4-Butanediol dimethacrylate

2-Butoxyethanol

2-Butoxyethyl acetate

Butterfly

n-Butyl acetate

sec-Butyl acetate

tert-Butyl acetate

n-Butyl alcohol

tert-Butyl chromate

Butyl dichlorophenoxyacetate

n-Butyl glycidyl ether

tert-Butyl hydroperoxide

Numerical Indexes

To provide access to information that is primarily numerical in nature, a numerical index may be compiled. Typical numerical indexes include statutory sections (e.g., U.S. Code or Bankruptcy Code), patent number indexes, contract number indexes, and parts number indexes.

To facilitate search within a written numerical index, such indexes are presented in numerical order, from the lowest to the highest number.

Occasionally, the identifiers may be formed from a combination of letters and numbers in a standard format, such as xx-000x0x, where “x” is a letter and “0” is a number. In that case, ordering of the identifier should be done by considering each digit of the number in turn, comparing first digits, then second digits, etc., until the appropriate order of items is determined.

For example, the following is a selection from an index to ACDelco vehicle parts (see www.competitiveautoparts.com/spreadsheets/acdelcosparkplugs.xls), in this case oil filters and spark plugs:

PF47

PF52

PFL400A

R42LTS

R42LTSM

R42T

R43

R43S

R43T

R43TS

R43TS6

R43TSK

R44T

R45TSX

R45XLS

R45XLS6

R46SZ

Notice that for each digit, numbers are “alphabetized” before letters.

In another example, the U.S. federal government uses a two-part identifier for forms: The first part of the form number is a two- or three-digit letter identifier that indicates the issuing department and the second part is the form number within that department. The form number itself may be a combination of numbers and letters. See the following (partial) list of form numbers from the U.S. Department of Labor (www.forms.gov/bgfPortal/openPage.jsp?fileId=0&URL=http://www.dol.gov/libraryforms/index.asp):

DOL-2000-7

DOL-2000-38

DOL-4000-9

DOL-9035CP

DOL-CA-10

DOL-CA-1108

DOL-CA-12

DOL-CA-17

DOL-CA-2

DOL-CA-20

DOL-CA-2231

DOL-CA-35

DOL-CC-4

DOL-CM-1093

DOL-CM-1159

DOL-DOLRNO-1

DOL-EEOICP EE-1

DOL-EEOICP EE-2

Melodic Indexes

Although there are numerous melodic indexes, especially to the works of individual classical composers such as Bach or Haydn, there is still no single established system of melodic indexing. We will discuss several possible systems here and comment on their significant drawbacks. In general, all rely on using some form of transcribing a relatively few initial notes (often eight) of the full melody. This usually serves sufficiently to disambiguate and identify specific works:

Numerical musical index – Use the number 1 to represent the tonic note of the melody, then use the appropriate numbers to identify the first eight (or so) notes of the melody. The melodies thus transcribed are then “alphabetized,” or in this case, put in numerical order by first note, then by second note, etc. One drawback of this method is that the listener may remember the start of the melody, but may not recognize the tonic note, and thus ends up looking for the wrong sequence.
Transposed letter index – Transpose the tune as if it were in C major or C minor, then use the appropriate letters (A–G) to identify the melody. Alphabetize on the first letter, then the second, etc.
Direct letter index – Transcribe the melody as written. Then alphabetize the melodies beginning with all that start with the letter “A,” then alphabetize on the second note: A-A, A-B, A-C, etc. Obviously, this method presents a significant problem, namely, that if a single melody has been given in a transposed edition, either by the composer or an arranger, then the two melodies will start on different notes and thus be considered two different works, making identification difficult for the listener.

Most melodic indexes ignore octave differences. Thus middle C and the C above middle C (usually given in musical notation as “c”) are both identified as “C.” This may conflate two melodies that contain notes that are actually in different octaves, making it difficult for the listener to find the specific melody.

In a review of The Greig-Duncan Folk Song Collection (Musical Traditions magazine, www.mustrad.org.uk/reviews/greigdun.htm, March 13, 2007) the unnamed reviewer notes these problems with the musical index:

It is a great pity that no standard method of melodic indexing has been established. Personally I find Charles Gore’s system in his invaluable The Scottish Fiddle Music Index the most accurate and revealing. It is based on Breandan Breathnach’s scheme, and recognises only on-beat notes and represents them by numbers, but it does rely on identifying which is the key note, represented in the index by the number 1.

The system used by Fleischmann in Sources of Irish Traditional Music avoids identifying the key note but assumes each tune starts on the note G. This is fine if you have a stable first note, but this is frequently not the case; and the system of indicating in which octave a note lies is confusing. Katherine Campbell’s method of entering repeated notes is economical, allowing more of the shape of the tune to show through and thus avoiding a flaw in Fleischmann’s method: but she has not specified the direction of octave leaps, and leaps in excess of the octave are not indicated at all.

The old system of Barlow and Morgenstern’s A Dictionary of Musical Themes was set up for Classical Music, for which it works tolerably well. In this system you mentally transpose your phrase into the key of C (major or minor), without necessarily establishing the key of the tune as a whole. The method employed here is similar to this last. It is that of entering the first eight notes as though the melody were in the key of C. However, Campbell’s note describing how to use the Melodic Index does not mention that minor key tunes should be thought of as in C minor…. Many people looking for an archetypal minor key on the white notes of a keyboard will automatically think of A minor.

The problem is that the researcher is probably not starting with the tune as it appears here, but with some unidentified tune the key of which (if any) is not immediately apparent …

The Melodic Index suffers from another difficulty in that it includes up-beats which are not indicated as such, and whose presence or absence in traditional music is unpredictable. Fleischmann enters tunes with and without their up-beats—a distinct advantage. For example, taking the above tune, even if you know it has an up-beat for the initial word “And,” it is quite likely that the version in your head has only the first of the two notes given to it in Greig-Duncan, so you might be searching for it as Bflat Eflat F G F Eflat F G. In other words, this Melodic Index is a rough tool.

Because a musical index is often a scholarly work in and of itself, the editor will generally determine the specific style of transcription to be used in the index. Editors should be aware, however, of the various systems of musical indexing possible and their inherent problems.

Citation Indexes

Citation indexes provide access to information in the references of a document. Most often citation indexes are based on citations of scholarly work in the sciences or the humanities. Psychology books typically have separate name indexes to accommodate citations. Citation indexes may also be found in other fields. For example, patent citation indexes reflect how often a specific patent is cited in later patents.

One of the earliest and still current citation indexes is the Science Citation Index, now published by Thomson Scientific and available online as the Web of Science.

By using citation indexes, users can follow citations backward in time, starting with the citations contained in a specific article or document. Users can also discover which articles written after the target document cite that document.

Chapter 3

Characteristics of a Good Index

One of the most important jobs an editor or author has to do in connection with an index is evaluate the index after it has been submitted by the indexer. However, this task can be complicated by the fact that editors and authors may have little training in how indexes are or should be constructed. Accordingly, they often complain they have little basis for evaluating the index.

This chapter discusses the specific characteristics of a good index. Looking for these characteristics can form the process for evaluating an index.

Additional information on various stylistic issues can be found in Chapter 4, which also includes a checklist for evaluating indexes.

ADHERENCE TO HOUSE STYLE

If a publisher has developed a specific in-house style for indexes, then the first layer of evaluation is to make sure that the index adheres to that style.

A house style sheet should at a minimum cover the following issues and include an example of each:

Capitalization (or not) of first word in headings
Alphabetization (word-by-word or letter-by-letter)
Headnote (allowable or not)
Preferred style (indented or paragraph/run-in style)
Number of levels of subheadings allowed
Placement of cross-references (after main heading, as first subheading, or as last subheading)
Handling of any special characters
Indexable material: Are the following to be included? If yes, is there any special treatment for their locators?

- Footnotes or endnotes

- Appendices

- Bibliography

- Illustrations, maps, artwork, photographs

- Tables, charts

If the index does not meet house style in some particular aspect, it is helpful to ask the indexer why he did not follow house style in that instance. The indexer should be able to point to some particular idiosyncrasy of the text in question that prompted the deviation from house style. Of course, it is advisable for the indexer to discuss with the editor or author the need for such a deviation when the issue first arises during the indexing process.

AUDIENCE SUITABILITY

The index should be suitable for its intended audience. That is, the index should use terminology that the intended audience would use.

This is especially important when dealing with technical materials. For example, in a medical text, the term “oncology” would be preferred, while in a book for the general public, oncology might be too technical and “cancer” used instead.

If there is any doubt about what terminology a book’s audience uses, then use cross-references:

felines. See cats

or double-postings (putting the same information in two places):

cats, 5, 28, 41

…

felines (cats), 5, 28, 41

In the case of the preceding double-posting, the qualifier “(cats)” after “felines” alerts users to the fact that an alternate term is used in the text.

In addition to using audience-appropriate terminology, an index should use a structure that is also appropriate for its intended audience. For example, an index intended to be used by elementary school students should probably not have six or seven levels of subheadings.

TREATMENT OF METATOPIC

In her book Facing the Text (2004), author Do Mi Stauber discusses the idea of a book’s “metatopic,” that is, the overarching subject that the book is generally about. The metatopic needs to be handled carefully in the index.

For example, in a book about whales, the entire index could conceivably contain one entry for “whales,” with the entire remainder of the index consisting of various subheadings and sub-subheadings. Obviously, such an index is useless to the reader. Accordingly, the metatopic becomes the assumed subject of the index. Hence, the index to our hypothetical book about whales would be better if it used such main headings as “communication,” “diet,” “mating habits,” “migration,” and so forth.

By default, in this hypothetical “whale” index, diet means the diet of whales, and migration means the migration of whales. The only entries that should be under the heading of “whales” itself are general entries that would fit nowhere else or would not make sense as their own main heading, such as “definition of” or “description of.”

SUBJECT COVERAGE

Check the index to make sure that all expected topics are included; the index should provide appropriate coverage of those discussions.

While the index should certainly cover all of the substantial topics in the text, as well as subsidiary topics, that coverage should reflect the relative length at which each topic is discussed. For example, if there are two chapters of approximately equal length, but one chapter topic has five entries in the index, and the second chapter topic has 57 entries, that may indicate a problem with the balance of the index’s subject coverage.

Comparing the index with the table of contents is one way to do a quick coverage check.

EXHAUSTIVITY

In addition to all the major subjects, all minor subjects should be included in the index at an appropriate level of coverage. However, the index should not include references to passing mentions, that is, mere mentions of the existence of something that do not provide readers with at least one fact that they might want to know. Scene-setting or time markers are examples of passing mentions.

While in general, exhaustivity of indexes is preferred, the depth of indexing is directly related to the space available for an index. Clearly, allowing only four pages for the index to an 800-page encyclopedia is doing its readers a disservice. The exhaustivity in such a brief index could not come close to the level that would really make it useful.

In discussing ways to add space for the index, Clive Pine notes on his Web site (www.cpynebookindexing.com/length_of_index.htm) that: “One or two blank pages usually found between the end of the text and the index might be used for the index. Just one page will make a big difference in index depth and usefulness.” Indeed, depending on the specific page size, adding one page may be adding a hundred or more pieces of information to the index.

Chapter 5 discusses the issue of index length specifically in greater detail.

DIFFERENTIATED LOCATORS

There is nothing more daunting to readers than long strings of undifferentiated locators, such as this example from the index to Maryland: A History of its People by Suzanne Ellery Green Chappelle, et al.:

Cereal crops, 10, 16–17, 23, 33–34, 36–37, 40, 42–43, 74–75, 81, 87, 91, 109, 112–117, 119, 124, 135, 140–141, 143, 173, 200–201, 221, 232–33, 273–74

The problem is that no user (or at least the vast majority of users) will ever take to time to visit each of those pages if they are looking for a specific fact about cereal crops in Maryland.

A good index will use appropriate subheadings to supply the context for specific mentions if there are more than a small number of references (say five or six) to a single topic.

WELL-FORMED SUBHEADINGS

Subheadings give the specific context in which the main heading is discussed at a particular location in the text. Accordingly, the indexer should clearly establish the relationship between the heading and subheading.

Sometimes the relationship is obvious:

alabaster

hardness, 12

But in other cases, the heading and subheading need clarification:

Napoleon

Russia, 128, 273

Here the exact nature of the relationship between Napoleon and Russia is unclear. Is the text about Napoleon in Russia? Is it about Napoleon’s thoughts or views on Russia? There is no way to tell with this single-word subheading.

Often it only takes the inclusion of a preposition to clarify the relationship:

Napoleon

in Russia, 128, 273

In a well designed index, the heading/subheading relationship will always be clear and obvious.

HEADNOTES

Whenever an index includes any nonstandard usages or employs special typography to indicate certain types of references, then the index should include an explanatory headnote, which appears on the first page of the index. Headnotes can consist of a single simple statement:

References to major discussions are in bold.

Or, they may be quite complex. The headnote to the index to Latham and Matthew’s edition of the Pepys Diary (London: Bell & Hyman, 1970–1983) is four and a half pages long.

What is important is that a headnote allows the user to understand any unusual features that are included in the index or to know particular information about how the index was compiled that might affect use of the index. For example:

This index uses Portuguese spellings of all place names.

or

This index is alphabetized on a letter-by-letter basis (ignoring spaces between words).

Headnotes should cover the following information, where appropriate:

Special typography
Use of special abbreviations
Issues of inclusion or exclusion, e.g., place names not indexed
Special subject matter treatment, e.g., all information on Virginia Stephens will be found under her married name (Virginia Woolf)
Explanation of how complex locators are formed, e.g., year-volume-page
Method of alphabetization
References to other indexes, if the volume contains more than one

DOUBLE-POSTING

Synonyms

As was mentioned previously under the topic of audience suitability, good indexes use double-posting. That is, the same subheads and locators are duplicated under two or more different terms that convey the same concept.

M. Ivonen noted in a 1995 paper (“Consistency in the selection of search concepts and search terms,” Information Processing & Management 31[2], 180–186) that users employ different terminology to identify the same concepts. As a result multiple access points are important in ensuring that users find the information they are looking for.

Because double-posting does increase the size of an index, it may sometimes be preferable to use cross-references. See the cross-references section that follows for more details.

Complex Topics

In addition, double-posting should also be used in cases where two related concepts are discussed. For example, if the text discusses the topic of class in Britain, the two ideas (the subject, “class,” and the location, “Britain”) should both appear in the index, with the heading and subheading flipped:

Britain

class in, 176

…

class

in Britain, 176

For especially complex subjects, as often happens in scholarly works or encyclopedias, triple- or quadruple-posting is not unusual:

Aristotle

soul, views on, comparison with Plato’s

…

Plato

soul, views on, comparison with Aristotle’s

…

soul

comparison of Plato’s and Aristotle’s views on

In such cases, it is important that all of the locators match in each of these parallel entries.

APPROPRIATE CROSS-REFERENCES

Cross-references comprise the syndetic structure of the index, that is, the connective tissue that helps build the structure of the index. A good index will include an appropriate number of cross-references, which come in two flavors: see references and see also references. An index with no cross-references at all should be viewed with suspicion.

See References

See references tell readers that the concept they are looking for is discussed in the text, but that the index (and the text) uses an alternate term for the concept. The reader will be able to find information in the index by looking at the referenced term. The term used in the index is referred to as the “preferred” or “postable” term, while the unused term is often called an “entry term.”

Note that a see reference never contains locators; its use is to direct readers to the place in the index that will lead to information in the text. (Because indexing is context-based, it reflects guidelines rather than rules. However this is one of the few rules applicable to all contexts.)

As already noted, see references may be used in place of double-posting to save space, or when the information presented under the preferred term is so extensive that it would unbalance the index to double-post the entire series of subheadings and locators under additional terms.

Synonyms

A good indexer will try to identify terms that users might use for concepts discussed in the text and then employ those alternate terms as additional entry points in the index.

See references take the following form:

a. See b

where “a” is the unused term and “b” is the preferred term.

Names

See references are often used in the cases of names, for example:

Stephens, Virginia. See Woolf, Virginia

which leads the user from the maiden name to this individual’s married name, which is used as the main heading in the index for this person.

Name see references may also be used in the case of pseudonyms:

Twain, Mark. See Clemens, Samuel

or in the case of countries that change names:

Yugoslavia. See Bosnia-Herzegovina; Croatia; Macedonia; Montenegro; Serbia; Slovenia

Generic References

In some cases, generic cross-references may be used, which lead readers not to a specific entry, but to a series or type of entries, for example:

American Indians. See names of specific tribes

It is then up to the user to identify the appropriate entries to look for. Depending on the sophistication of the user or the general audience, it may be more helpful to provide a direct see reference, even if the list of entry terms spans several lines:

American Indians. See Apache; Cherokee; Choctaw; Hopi; Iroquois; Lakota; Lumbee; Navajo; Oglala; Pueblo; Sioux; Ute; Zuni

A good index will also use see references for the secondary concept in headings that comprise two related but opposite concepts, such as “life and death.” An appropriate see reference would be:

death. See life and death

Because users generally scan an index looking for terms, they may not always catch a secondary term that does not appear at the left margin.

Acronyms

Terms such as UNICEF and UN are acronyms. The indexer should use the generally accepted form of the acronym and then refer readers to its alternate:

IMF. See International Monetary Fund

Inverted Phrases

When a term consists of a phrase that can be logically inverted, include an appropriate see reference:

malpractice, medical. See medical malpractice

See Also References

See also references let the user know that additional related information is included at a number of other places in the index. A good index will identify related concepts for the reader by providing appropriate see also references, leading users to additional relevant information given under terms that they might not think of immediately. See also references take the form:

a, 12, 48. See also b; c; d

where “a” is the referring term and “b,” “c,” and “d” are the objects of the reference. Note that the see also reference comes after any locators.

If the entry has subheadings, the see also reference may be placed (1) after the main heading, (2) as the first subheading, or (3) as the last subheading:

Native Americans. See also politics and Native Americans; trade and Native Americans; women, Native American

activism, 341–342

as artists, 276–278

or

Native Americans.

See also politics and Native Americans; trade and Native Americans; women, Native American

activism, 341–342

as artists, 276–278

or

Native Americans

activism, 341–342

as artists, 276–278

…

as writers

See also politics and Native Americans; trade and Native Americans; women, Native American

Placement up front can help trigger ideas for the users. End placement serves as a “last resort” for users unable to find relevant information in the current array.

In general, see also references should lead users from a more general index entry to more specific index entries, as well as related information at the same level of generality:

history

…

See also historians; medieval period; Renaissance

However, there is some disagreement on this issue; a significant number of indexers hold that see also references should work in both directions: general to specific and specific to general.

Cross-Reference Validation

As part of an index review, the editor should examine the cross-references for the following problems:

Blind cross-references (which refer the reader to nonexistent headings)
Circular cross-references:

bovines. See cows

…

cows. See bovines

Wrong cross-reference type: see instead of see also and vice versa

INDEX REVIEWS

In addition to ensuring that an index adheres to the preceding characteristics, there are a number of reviews that an editor should perform to ensure a high quality index:

Verify alphabetical order of all entries
Proofread the index for correct spelling
Spot-check a certain percentage of index entries to be sure that the designated pages actually discuss the referring subject

See Chapter 9 for additional details on editing a completed index.

Chapter 6

Author/Editor/Indexer Relationships

To paraphrase Casablanca, every index is potentially the beginning of a beautiful relationship. It may be a simple, businesslike, two-person dialogue between an editor and an indexer; it may be a sweeping soap opera involving a cast of lead editor, production editor, compositor, subject indexer, names indexer, author, and the author’s secretary and graduate students. Wherever the indexing process occurs along that continuum, however, it involves the development of a relationship. That relationship can be mutually profitable and can lead to further collaborations, or it can be toxic. Like all relationships, it requires some work on the part of all parties involved.

Honesty and fairness are critical to the development of a satisfactory author/editor/indexer partnership. All parties will find the process much smoother if they are up-front about what they want from the index, what restrictions they have, and when things need to be done.

Authors are disadvantaged because, even as seasoned writers, they have gone through the publication process with only a limited number of books. As a result, they sometimes make assumptions about what the index should include. It is a little late to ask for a complete index of names or to have the notes indexed after receiving the final index. By then, the indexer has moved on to other projects, and the editor has to get the book into production or to the printer. Authors with firm ideas about the index should talk to either the editor or the indexer, or preferably both, at the start of the process to make sure they will get what they want.

Editors are like the umpires at a ball game; they need to be clear on the rules, things like house style requirements and when the index is due. Nothing frustrates an indexer more than to be told, when turning in a completed index, “Oh, did I tell you? We only have eight pages. You may have to cut.” It is much easier to produce the required index when the indexer knows about space restrictions right at the start. Waiting until the very end of the process—or, worse, making executive decisions on the sly and hoping no one will notice—is not fair to anyone, least of all the text being indexed.

THE IMPORTANCE OF COMMUNICATION

A co-author of this book once pointed out to a client that she needed to have final pages before she could begin indexing; if the text moved around on the pages, she would need to reindex all or part of the work and would have to charge accordingly. About a quarter of the way through the indexing process, someone decided the book should be printed with a larger font size, which naturally affected the flow of the text across the pages, changing the page numbers for quite a few entries.

Instead of talking to the indexer about this, the editor said nothing, let her keep indexing, and decided to fix the pagination differences in-house after submission—except it never got fixed. When the publisher sent the indexer a copy of the book, she immediately realized that three quarters of the page numbers were off, and a comparison of the printed book with the manuscript she had saved soon showed why.

The indexer contacted the editor, who confessed that she had been “afraid” to contact her and figured she would charge more money, busting her budget. In fact the indexer could have repaginated the entries pretty easily, for a minimal extra charge. As it turned out, the editor paid full price for a completely useless index.

In the rarest of instances, an index has to be revised and reprinted separately, costing even more. A little communication early in the game will help mitigate such crises.

POTENTIAL PROBLEMS WITH AN INDEX

Indexers, on their part, owe it to their clients to quickly determine if a manuscript presents special problems, such as missing figures, sliding schedules, mispaginations, misplaced illustrations, etc., particularly if such problems will affect scheduling and cost. The indexer should discuss these issues frankly with the editor and author. Even if they are contacted only verbally or by email, indexers have a contract with their clients to produce an acceptable work in a certain amount of time for a particular price.

It is not uncommon to reach an agreement for indexing without the indexer having seen a truly representative sample of the text. On examination, the text may present difficulties that were not clear at the time of accepting the project. A linguistics text, for example, might turn out to contain computational materials that the indexer did not expect and has no clue how to handle. The project may turn out a good deal longer than originally indicated, which could affect schedule and budget.

If a project is submitted well ahead of its due date, it is a good idea to try to index at least a chapter to get a feel for the book and its particular issues. That way, if you see a potential problem, you can tell the editor and author about it right away and have time to work through how to handle it.

Besides honesty and fairness, authors, editors, and indexers also need to recognize and respect each other’s roles in the publishing process. Failure to understand and appreciate what different parties bring to the finalization of the text is at the heart of many a wayward project. Authors, editors, and indexers share some ends, but they also have divergent goals. Comprehending these legitimate differences and keeping them in mind will be of enormous assistance in creating and sustaining a successful collaboration.

THE INDEX FROM THREE POINTS OF VIEW

Authors and Indexes

Authors are not always much involved in the indexing process. Some publishing houses handle indexing entirely through the editors or the production department, especially if the publisher is handling payment. If authors get any chance at all to comment on the index, their remarks are dealt with entirely in-house. In other situations, the indexer gets author feedback, but only through the agency of the editor.

Sometimes a press may have a list of “recommended indexers” to give an author and expect authors and indexers to communicate directly with each other; in some cases the author even contracts with and pays the indexer directly. So it is important for editors and indexers to understand the special needs and situation of the author.

Indexers and editors need to know two crucial things about authors. First, books are like the authors’ children. Authors may have spent two to three years, and often far, far longer, researching the subject and writing the text. Especially if it is their first published text, authors are often excited and concerned about every aspect of its publication, including the index.

It is often a terrible shock for authors to discover that for the editor and indexer, their baby is just another job, another item on their busy schedules. Ironically, both the editor and the indexer are likely to be paid far more for their relatively brief involvement with texts than most authors will ever make from them. For 99 percent of authors, their publication becomes chiefly a labor of love. So if authors seem to be fussing over tiny details—obsessing over the precise wording of a minor array or dithering over how exactly to format cross-references—remember, you are likely to be talking about the equivalent of their beloved first-born.

The second crucial thing to remember about authors is that, in all likelihood, they know nothing about indexing. The indexer will have to explain basic indexing facts, such as the rules of double-posting versus cross-referencing, and what is considered indexable material. Like any other group of individuals, some authors “get” indexing right away, and some never will, so the explanatory process may be simple or quite involved.

Some authors happily sit back and let indexers do their work, but many—whom one might optimistically refer to as “high-energy tinkerers”—will insist upon reading through the index line by line. To pretty much anyone but an indexer, reading an index rather than consulting it is a confusing process. Authors who do this will inevitably have questions, many of which may arise from ignorance of the indexing process.

Authors may jump to bizarre conclusions about the way the index works. Some authors will assume they need to check every page reference in the index and then get bogged down in trying to figure out exactly where a subject begins and ends (something that all indexers know is often open to interpretation).

Important Topics for Authors

The following topics are those that most consistently raise questions from authors. The indexer or editor needs to provide straightforward explanations. Here are some examples:

Why are some topics in two places, while other topics are cross-referenced? Small amounts of information are “double-posted,” or are put in every place the reader might look for them, for ease of use. We only cross-reference to large chunks of information. For example, I have cross-referenced any array with more than three (or five, or whatever) subheadings.
Some things are in the index twice. There is an entry for farming so why then do we have an entry for agriculture? That is redundant! Indexes are supposed to be redundant. They are intended to provide all reasonable points of entry into a text. A person who wants to find information about agriculture will look in the A’s; he might not think to look under farming. Remember, readers do not read the index; they consult it. Someone who looks up agriculture will likely never even know there is a “redundant” entry for farming. When there are two such entries, it is also important that the same information is in both places.
The index has entries for my colleague Fred on page 32, but I reference his book in several notes in chapter 2. Why aren’t those indexed? The index only provides entries for substantive information. The references to Fred’s book in the notes are not considered substantive—you have simply indicated it as a source for the information you talk about in the text. On page 32, however, you talk quite expansively about Fred’s theories. That is considered substantive material. Sometimes authors make a special request for a complete names index, covering every scholarly mention in the text. This is the type of request that needs to come at the start of the project.
The main topic of my book is whales, but there’s hardly anything in the index under whales! The main topic of the book, what indexers call the “metatopic,” is what every entry in the index is about. The metatopic provides the unspoken context of the index. The reader knows this and will only look up “whales” in the index for certain sorts of things, such as kinds or types of whales, or the definition of a whale. Otherwise, every entry would be under whales.

Author-Editor and Author-Indexer Relationships

Editors and indexers can avoid some of these complications by dealing with author questions before they arise. By the time indexing rolls around, editors will have figured out what kind of authors they are dealing with and what kind of involvement in the index they will want. If not, editors should ask authors an openended question about their requirements regarding the index to gauge their anticipated level of involvement. The editor should then make sure when setting up the job to inform the indexer how the author will be involved.

Indexers who know they will be working directly with authors should make sure to ask a few pertinent questions right up front. What kinds of things does the author expect to appear in the index? What about names? Should the notes be indexed? Explaining all the options, and conveying how they affect timing and price and length, at the beginning of the indexing process ensures fewer surprises or disappointments later. When the index is done, “fixing” it to the extent desired might not be possible.

Author Term Lists

Authors sometimes produce, on their own or at the behest of an editor, a list of key terms they expect to see in the index. This can be a simple and short guide or practically an index in itself (just without page numbers). Editors and authors seem to imagine that they are saving the indexer time and trouble. We regret to say that they are not. Indexers generally dislike key term lists.

Often, 80 percent of the terms on such lists are totally obvious (“Darwin, Charles” and “morality, origins of,” for instance, for a book entitled Evolution and Christian Ethics). About 15 percent are terms that no seasoned indexer would put in an index as a main heading (“related subjects”). And 5 percent are terms that, search as he might, the indexer cannot even find in the text: It is not unheard of for authors to believe they have written about something when they actually have not. Another possibility is that the phrase or sentence containing that term was removed in editing.

Both authors and editors sometimes seem to be under the mistaken apprehension that indexers work by thinking up terms and then looking for them in the text. If that were the case, using a keyword list might make some sense. But in fact, indexers do their job by reading the text from start to finish and finding or formulating terms from that process. So the keyword list generally offers little help in the process, although maybe it serves as a validation tool.

Authors and editors wedded to the idea should consider this option: Make up a list of no more than 35 terms that are considered crucial to the text. By making the list a matter of choice and restriction rather than all-inclusive, authors will provide the indexer with a useful and manageable guide to what they deem most important in the text.

If it is house policy to require author evaluation of the index, we recommend the publisher have an instruction sheet about the process. Many publishing houses furnish handouts about how to index, but few have guidelines for index evaluation. Publishers can avoid a great deal of time and trouble by developing such a set of guidelines on their own or by working with their regular indexers.

As an example, a publisher might require a cross-reference to all acronyms, even if there is only one page number; both the author and the indexer need to know such a requirement.

See Chapter 9 in this book for more information about developing evaluation guidelines. For their part, indexers working directly with authors may want to develop their own evaluation guidelines for the author.

Authors will help the indexing part of the editorial process go much more smoothly if they make sure they understand what they are expected to do in terms of review, and if they stick to the review schedule. A book one indexer once worked on missed its print date—and the conference at which it was supposed to be a featured text—because the author failed to approve the index on time, even though he had received it well before the deadline and had no significant changes to make to it.

While the nonappearance of the book was a nuisance for the author at the conference, it was the editor who had to deal with most of the fallout, and it was the editor and her publishing house that looked bad, even though the delay was beyond their control.

Editors and Indexes

When it comes to indexes, editors are a bit like traffic cops at the end of rush hour. They are near the end of the project, and they are hoping to get the index through the intersection and on its way without any accidents. This is not to say that editors do not value quality; they are some of the few people on earth who consciously appreciate really good indexing when they see it. But they also have a schedule to keep and a budget to manage—and by the time the indexing part of the project rolls around, that schedule and budget may have been stretched to their limits already, and both indexers and editors have to appreciate that fact.

Sometimes the indexing part of the publication process can be compared to a child’s playground game of crack-the-whip. Just as the end child absorbs the full force of the energy coursing from wrist to wrist, so the indexing process bears the brunt of all the delays and overruns of costs and pages that have occurred throughout the project, simply by happening at the end.

If this is true for textual editors, it is true in spades for production editors. They specialize in shepherding a finished text through the stages required for it to appear in print. Indexers dealing with production editors often innocently assume that they know the content of a book as well as the textual editor does; but while the production editors can confidently tell you about font, type size, page count, and scheduling, they may not be able to answer detailed questions about subject matter. For that, the indexer will need to contact the author or the original text editor. In other cases, the production editor funnels questions to authors and developmental editors.

So editors need indexers to understand the schedule and the budget, and to inform them as early as possible of any problems or conflicts. To keep editors happy—and to keep their business—indexers need to do four things:

Obtain all the needed information at the start, and ask for it if the editor does not provide it automatically
Perform a spot check of the project as soon as it comes in, even if the actual indexing would not be started for a while; ensure all the pages are present, all the files are readable, and that the project length and degree of difficulty match expectations
Inform the editor as soon as problems affecting scheduling or price arise
Turn the index in on time and in good shape (no typos, bad cross-references, etc.)

Indexers also need to not do one other thing: pester the editor. Probably the ideal situation for editors follows this scenario: book the indexer and send him the project, and hear nothing until the day before you have penciled yourself a note to make an inquiry, at which time the index file appears in your email box, needing essentially no corrections.

Indexers often have legitimate questions about errors they see in the text, whether certain things should be picked up or ignored, or the preferred formatting of certain items. But editors do not want to hear from indexers daily while they work on a project. They are busy, and one of the reasons they have hired a freelancer is because they want someone who can work independently.

Some indexers think that asking the editor a lot of questions shows interest and drive, and perhaps it does, but it will also assuredly drive the editor up the wall. Try to save up questions and ask them in a bunch, say once a week, unless the question truly requires immediate input to continue indexing. If working directly with an author, copy the editor on any email exchanges so she is kept informed of progress, but do not request editorial input unless it is genuinely needed.

Indexers and Indexes

If one were to do a study of logos on the business cards of indexers, one would find a disturbing number of woodcut reproductions showing earnest little monks laboring over illuminated manuscripts. Indexers like to think of themselves this way, and so, it seems, does much of the rest of the world (when it thinks about indexers at all). The stereotypical portrayals of indexers in novels and short stories show them as harmless drudges with no personal lives slaving for pennies over obscure texts. Authors and editors, however, should not buy into this fiction.

Indexers are professionals who generally run their own successful businesses. They work as indexers because they love books and language, and they love thinking for a living, but also because they happen to be good at a job few people can do well. They work very hard at acquiring, maintaining, and adding to their skills. And it is a skill.

Many bad indexes have been produced because an author figured a graduate student or a spouse could whip up an index in short order. Indexers want to do a good job, and they want to keep your business, but at the end of the day they also expect and need to make a decent living from it, and they need to deal with many clients.

Index Revisions

Indexers cannot drop everything to work on a single project. They usually juggle a number of jobs, and when the clients’ schedules slip, it may be necessary to compromise over type and timing of work. It also means they cannot afford to tinker endlessly over a job. We call these “vampire indexes”: projects you turn in but that keep coming back with new requests, such as add all the names in the notes or index subject matter in the notes; or now there is a space issue, so remove references to the notes or change the original specified formatting of the page numbers…. Inevitably, of course, these vampires rise from the undead just before press time and so require immediate attention.

An indexer will be happy to correct mistakes, make adjustments to the wording when requested, add or remove entries to meet the original specifications, and make some formatting corrections. But the editorial process should not, and cannot, run on endlessly. Editors and authors who find themselves going through more than two revisions of the index should ask themselves if the indexer is just not paying attention to requests, or whether it is they themselves who are prolonging the process by changing their minds or not being clear about what they want.

A vampire project can be easily avoided. How? Editors and authors should communicate properly with the indexer at the beginning of the project, making clear what they expect, what the schedule is, and what the publisher’s rubrics are.

A good indexer will make sure to ask the basic questions, of course, but the indexer cannot guess that the author wants only initials for first names of persons (even though they are given in full in the text), or that house style is to print references to illustrations in bold, italic font, or that the book is expected to be a big seller in Romania, so all references to Romania must be picked up, even if they are not substantive.

Authors and editors also need to realize that indexers are not production editors. The job of the indexer is primarily one of content, not formatting. See Chapter 4 on formatting for more information about what indexers can and cannot do, and on what a polished index should look like. While indexers use special software that can do amazing things in terms of manipulating data, such as adding volume numbers to page references and changing the punctuation between text and page reference globally, they do not produce camera-ready copy.

While the vampire index can be a pain in the neck, indexers do like to get feedback. Ours is a solitary profession. We mainly work alone, and often the only way we know an index was a success is that we never hear anything more about it once we have sent it in and payment arrives (and even then we may not be sure, until we get repeat business from the client). So while indexers are business people, we are also craftspeople who are willing to revise work to fit needs or to explain why we have made the choices we’ve made. If an author or editor does not understand why something appears the way it is, they should feel free to ask. Indexers are generally happy to inform editors and authors about the indexing process and functions.

Indexers work by rules and patterns that someone just looking at the index may not immediately recognize. A co-author of this text once opened a book to find that the index, a succession of single lines, many with no page references, was totally out of alphabetical order. It took a minute to realize that someone who did not understand the principles by which index lines are indented had left-justified all the subentries. If something in the index does not make sense to you, ask. The indexer will talk with you about it and make alternative suggestions, if necessary.

ESTABLISHING THE FACTS

The Schedule

Usually, an editor or author who needs an index contacts an indexer—someone the publishing house or a colleague has worked with; an indexer who has sent a solicitation to the publisher; or someone located through a Web site or from the in-house list of recommended indexers. (See Chapter 7 for more information on finding an indexer.) What do you need to convey in that first conversation for the relationship to get off to a good start?

The first thing you need to nail down is the scheduling, no matter at what stage in the publication process the book is. Publishing is a schedule-driven industry, and for an editor, an indexer who cannot make the schedule has little use, no matter how good he is. Indexers, for their part, work with many clients, and the good indexers have busy calendars; before they hear anything else, they need to know if there is any chance they can accommodate you. The scheduling often is the most frustrating part of the entire process.

Depending on how forward thinking the editor and author are, the indexer may be contacted well in advance of the proofs being available. When contacted early, the indexer will probably be able to fit the project in. In my experience, indexers are generally booked about six weeks out.

However, the earlier one tries to schedule the indexing process, the less likely it is that the schedule will be adhered to. Indexers accept that there will be a certain amount of slippage in the schedule—they have to—but editors and authors who line up indexers early should still be aware that if the project’s timeline goes pear-shaped, everyone may have to make some compromises as to deadlines.

Not infrequently, somebody forgets to book the index until the last minute. Precisely because many projects are delayed, indexers may be able to insert a project into their workload. Again, compromises may be required. So whoever contacts the indexer should be well apprised of the timeline, what is absolutely nonnegotiable in terms of deadlines, and where there might be some extra space.

When an author or editor calls or emails an indexer about doing an index, the conversation tends to go something like this:

Author or Editor: Can you index my book?

Indexer: When is it due?

Author or Editor: When could you finish it by?

This response might make the indexer grind her teeth, even though it is a perfectly reasonable question on its face. The fact is, if for an urgent project, the editor is willing to pay a rush fee, and the book is not too long, it can be done in a day or so. But the indexer might not like burning the midnight oil and ultimately could do a better job if given more time.

On the other hand, if the budget is tight, an indexer might be able to work on an index in bits and pieces when she has a few spare hours and finish it in a month for a good price. If the indexer has a lot of other work, she may not be able to work on it right away, but if the text is available now, she could take it and, if another project slips, could turn it around far earlier.

Normally it’s preferable to have a two-week window scheduled to work on a standard 250-page monograph, from reception of text to deadline, but really, the schedule ultimately depends on when the client needs it back. If you tell an indexer the deadline and the number of pages, she can tell you whether she can make it happen and how, and you can go from there.

Payment for the Index

Understandably, editors and authors usually want to know about pricing right up front, and generally so do indexers. While indexes can be priced as a lump sum for the project, by the hour, or even by number of entries in the finished index, 90 percent of the time indexers charge per page of indexable text. Rates very a great deal, depending on the indexer’s experience and skill, and the difficulty of the book. Encyclopedic, exhaustive indexes will definitely merit a higher per-page charge.

Most indexers will quote you an estimated price range and then confirm the actual per-page price when they have seen the text itself or a representative sample. If the client specifies an average number of entries per page, this helps in setting the price.

Indexers will also want to know who is in charge of paying: the editor or the author. The price will not differ, but some indexers prefer to institute a progressive payment schedule when working with an individual as opposed to a large company, perhaps receiving part of the fee at the time of the agreement, with the rest due on satisfactory completion of the work.

Editorial Responsibility

Indexers need to know whom to contact about the index, and who has editorial input and responsibility. Will a separate production editor be involved, and what questions should be addressed to her? Is the indexing being handled entirely by an editor, or is the author driving this particular bus? Will there be an index review as part of the process? The partnership will go along much more smoothly if all this information is shared right at the beginning of the project.

Subcontracting

Indexers usually work on their own. If, however, they are working on a project with a special component—the author has requested a full listing of all secondary source authors, for instance, or a separate list of Biblical citations which will be extensive, or if it is a legal index with a great many case citations requiring a separate table of cases—the indexer may bring in a subcontractor to work on that part of the project. The editor or author should be informed the indexer is doing this, in the interest of full disclosure, as there is a chance that it might affect scheduling or work processes at some point.

Different indexers have different work processes in regard to subcontractors, and as freelancers these procedures are theirs to arrange. But if subcontracting is likely to have an effect on indexing quality or scheduling, indexers should always be open with editors about it. Some publishing houses state in their contracts that they expect the work to be the sole product of the contracting indexer; if this is the case, it is especially important for the indexer to disclose subcontracting practices.

Contracts

Some publishing houses and some indexers always issue a formal contract for even the smallest jobs. In general, however, most projects are short-term and are agreed to in an informal letter or letters of intent (in most cases a series of emails, these days). This is a perfectly good way of doing business. Keep copies of email correspondence with clients for reference and in case a problem should arise; if necessary, these would provide legal evidence of any contractual arrangements.

For any large or long-term job, however, the best option is a formal contract, which should spell out payment arrangements, deadlines, and who shall decide the acceptability of the work and how that will be determined. You might also want to include information about contingencies like late payment fees or the effect of slippage in receipt of material on the date the index is due.

The American Society of Indexers (ASI) has a sample contract available on its Web site (asindexing.org/site/asiagree.htm), shown in Appendix A.

WORKING OUT THE DETAILS

Now that you have established a preliminary working relationship, what comes next? It is time to focus on details. Authors, editors, and indexers will all have questions about the project, and for this partnership to work, it is important not to be shy about asking them. It is also useful not to assume anything.

What the Indexer Needs

At the start of a project, an editor or an author will often ask, “What do you need from me?” Well, first of all, an indexer needs the text that is to be indexed. Only a few years ago, most indexers worked off hard copy, and editors spent a lot of money mailing out big packages of paper. Today most indexers get the text via an electronic download—usually in Adobe Acrobat PDF format, as an email attachment or downloaded from an FTP site.

Due to vision problems, one co-author of this book started indexing directly from the electronic source, which could be magnified, and quickly found it had other advantages: Long names or organizational names could be cut and pasted more quickly (and accurately) than retyping them, and the search function could be used to check for occurrences of indexable terms (especially useful for “hard targets,” e.g., names of countries, without synonyms or alternative forms). Many indexers still prefer to work mostly from paper, although most also take advantage of these electronic functions.

The indexer needs the text to be in its final, or nearly final, format. For one thing, if the text changes significantly after it has been indexed, the index would not reflect those changes. Text changes might affect the whole index too, because altering the text may change the way it flows over the pages. A chunk of text inserted into page 4 may relocate every bit of text that follows in the chapter and perhaps in the whole book. Topics once correctly indexed as being on page 5 may have shifted over to page 6. While very small changes and corrections to things like typos will usually not make a huge difference, editors and authors often underestimate how last-minute rewrites can affect the pagination.

Production editors may not change the text, but their layout work will often radically affect the way the text falls on the pages. Publishers may try to have the indexing done while production work is finalized, but this usually is a recipe for disaster. Unless your text is indexed to section numbers (which are fixed in relationship to the text regardless of how it is formatted), or you have worked out some other method of relating index entries to indexed text so that page numbers can be attached at some later date (usually by embedding the entries in the text), you will need to ensure that the indexer gets the final version of the text.

If the publishing house has style guidelines, whoever is working directly with the indexer should make sure that she has a copy. Indexers are used to working with a wide variety of styles and can easily adapt to them, sometimes even using their software to impose global style choices at the end of the indexing process. But many formatting and style requirements affect how the index is constructed, so the earlier an indexer knows how the index should look, the better. Style guidelines should be sent with the text to be indexed.

Most indexers will turn in the index as an electronic RTF file, readable in almost any word processing system. Editors and authors who require some other format should work out their needs with the indexer right at the beginning to save a mad scramble at the end of the project. Anyone with a working knowledge of word processing can alter fonts, margins, columns, etc., at will, and print the index out. Asking for these sorts of special features (as opposed to, say, requesting that the references to photographs be in italic type) is unnecessary. Clients will sometimes request that indexers turn in a paper copy, or double-space the index, or put it in double columns—all relics of the pre-digital age.

A text being indexed using embedded tags does, however, require special handling. See Chapter 10 for details on that subject.

Previewing an Index

Authors and sometimes editors, especially those handling their first project, occasionally will ask if they can preview an index. On the face of it this may sound sensible, but it is often not very helpful. A partially written index is not like a partially written book. While books have discrete portions, indexes do not. Entries in an index depend upon each other.

For instance, the indexer might come across a section about environmentalism in a text, and he knows from his first review of the text that this topic comes up quite a few times in the second half of the book. So he puts in an entry under environmentalism and inserts a cross-reference from “ecology.” Someone looking at the partial index might legitimately wonder why he has not double-posted this entry.

Partial indexes are also unedited. An indexer might be uncertain of how to word a complex concept, so he may have some sort of placeholder for it until he comes up with the mot juste; a reviewer would not understand what this shorthand meant. There will be lots of this sort of thing in a partial index. Editors and authors may become confused and worried when they see these things, and the indexer then has to spend precious time explaining and defending them.

Finally, the timetable will be affected by a partial review. If there are two deadlines for a project rather than just one, it affects the flexibility the indexer has to get it done and often takes longer, especially if he has to wait for the reviewer to give feedback before proceeding.

A co-author of this book once submitted a partial index for review only to get it back covered with worried notes about missing elements—all from the part of the book that had not yet been indexed. It turned out that when asking for a “partial index,” the reviewing author expected a complete index of the first half of the alphabet (another example, presumably, of a non-indexer assuming indexers work by thinking of terms and then looking for them in the text). The author had spent tons of time on his notes, and the editor and indexer then had to spend tons of time explaining matters.

Submission of a partial index may be a good idea if the project is a long one, taking several months. This is especially true if payment is to be made in partial installments as indexing progresses; the milestone submitted is a good-faith indication that the work is being done.

If the text deals with a complicated topic, and if the reviewer understands the basics of the indexing process, a partial index review arrangement can be useful. But in most cases, in short projects with tight turnaround times, review of partial indexes impedes progress more than helps. It is much better to review a finished index in its organic wholeness.

DEVELOPING AND SUSTAINING THE RELATIONSHIP

Everyone has the materials and information required, and all have come to a good understanding of what sort of index to expect, when it will be turned in, and to whom it will be submitted. So now you just sit back and wait for it, right? Well, in a perfect world, yes. But this world is seldom perfect. Big things happen: Schedules change, a production editor needs to reflow the pages, someone gets sick, etc. But more often lots of little things happen: The indexer runs across a sentence that seems garbled; the author feels a bit uncertain about precisely what is going to be indexed in the notes; the editor realizes he has booked a vacation the week the index is due.

Communicating efficiently during the period in which the index is being produced will develop and sustain the author/editor/indexer relationship.

Prompt Notifications

Anything that will affect the schedule or the indexing process requires prompt notification. If the indexer finds that the work is not what he expected and will take longer than estimated, he must inform the editor immediately, and negotiations based on the new reality must occur. If the editor’s schedule shifts, and the index will be needed earlier, the editor should talk to the indexer as soon as possible and see what can be arranged. Sometimes, the project has to be moved to another indexer, so the sooner the editor or author knows about the schedule change, the better to find someone.

Most people in publishing are aware of the fluid nature of project timing, but no one can be infinitely flexible. Dealing with scheduling issues as soon as they arise is the best way to make sure the work gets done.

Holding Back

As mentioned previously, there is such a thing as too much communication. Indexers should not pester editors with questions, and editors and authors should let the indexer get on with the work. Nevertheless, questions arise: typos or spelling inconsistencies in the text, queries about coverage, stylistic issues, whether to include parenthetical explanations (for instance, “Diocletian (Roman emperor), 352, 689”), etc.

Unless an answer is absolutely needed, the best option is to save these queries, and either report on them at the end or, for a longer project, send them to the editor or author in an email every week or so. An indexer should always try to indicate how a response will affect the index, and whether she really needs a definite answer, or if she is just informing the editor or author of a typo.

For their part, authors and editors need to respond to such communications promptly if an answer is needed. Sometimes an indexer sends off a critical note (“Both Greek and Roman forms of town names are used in the text. Do you have a preference as to how you want these listed in the index?”), and it is as if the email fell off the ends of the earth. In such situations, the indexer needs to make a judgment call, note what she has done, and hope the client will agree with her decision. If it has to be fixed at the end, it may add unnecessary time to the project.

Occasionally, clients become rather huffy when the indexer points out an error. The indexer should try to be as diplomatic as possible and hope authors and editors will respond in kind. Everyone makes mistakes; no text is perfect, just as no index is perfect. Indexers tend to notice rather different sorts of errors than a proofreader; for instance, we are more likely to spot spelling inconsistencies many pages or chapters away from each other as we pick up references to names or places. The proofer is more likely to spot inconsistencies right near one another. It is important to remember that everyone’s aim is to produce the best book possible.

Wrapping It All Up

Often indexers submit an index and never hear another thing; the index is published with little or no change. Sometimes, however, editors—and especially authors—want to make corrections and revisions to the index. Indexers generally welcome this process. Often, however, revision work means that indexers have to educate authors and editors about indexing. Indexers have to be prepared for this, and their clients have to be prepared to listen. When indexers get feedback on an index, it generally involves three sorts of issues:

Things that must be corrected
Changes in wording
Queries and comments related to the way the index works

Yes, indexers do make mistakes, and when they are picked up, the indexer should readily fix them. Authors and editors should expect the occasional error; that is one of the reasons someone familiar with the book should review the index. Remember, the indexer has probably come across and reported typos and errors in the text, even after it has been proofread, so it is not surprising that some errors may crop up in the index as well.

While a high rate of error is a problem, obviously, finding one or two should not be viewed as the end of the world, but as par for the course. Again, we are all trying to produce the best work possible, and corrections should be taken in stride.

Clients sometimes prefer different wording from what the indexer has used. Unless the indexer finds it to be problematic (it does not make sense, or it makes the line impossibly long and cumbersome), he should accept whatever a client prefers. The author’s or editor’s fresh eye may have revealed a simpler and clearer way of expressing an idea, and the indexer needs to be open to that.

Probably 80 percent of the queries a reviewer sends, however, have to do with the way the index is constructed. The client does not understand why or when cross-referencing versus double-posting is used, or why different forms of cross-references are entered, or the difference between a page reference that is a range (97–99) versus one that is a series (97, 98, 99). The indexer’s job includes explaining why she made those choices and what the alternatives are, and the reviewer’s job is to understand those explanations.

An indexer may want to provide notes for the reviewer if there are unusual features or if she feels something is not self-explanatory. Nevertheless, it frequently happens that the indexer will get a query such as, “For some reason, some of the pages are in italics. I think the file may be corrupted.” An indexer may then have to point out that the index headnote indicates that italic page references indicate illustrations (a common indexing convention).

That is not to say that every choice the indexer has made is not alterable. Most index structures are malleable, and there are many ways to put an index together. A good indexer will give the author or editor choices about how to solve a particular indexing problem. But clients themselves, when they are reviewing an index, need to be aware that indexers usually have good reasons for why they have done something and that the index does indeed have a logical structure.

Part of the great fun of indexing is its puzzle-like construction. If authors and editors are open to learning about indexing, and indexers are open to discussing their process, the review and finalization of the index can be a rewarding process.

A satisfying index review is both the end and the beginning of a relationship. When authors, editors, and indexers understand each other’s priorities, respect each other’s abilities, and are honest and open in their dealings, they will be able to move through the indexing part of the publishing process quickly and easily. And a successful first project together may lead to many more.

Chapter 7

Hiring an Indexer

USING A PROFESSIONAL INDEXER

Some authors may be tempted to save money by employing a family member or a graduate student (for scholarly works) to prepare the index to their text. Others may even consider writing the index themselves. In both cases, this is usually a bad idea. It is rare for anyone to have the native ability to create a good index. Usually, it takes considerable training, either through a course or course plus mentorship, to understand how best to build the structure of a good index.

In addition, professional indexers get better with experience. After having written dozens, if not hundreds, of indexes, they will have already faced most of the complexities to be found in any text. They will have an arsenal of techniques at hand that allow them to focus on the text itself, rather than on strictly technical matters.

Members of professional indexing societies, such as the American Society of Indexers (ASI), are also able to take advantage of continuing education programs through local chapters, as well as at annual national conferences. Local and regional chapters often have regular peer review sessions that help individual indexers continue to improve their skills.

Experienced professional indexers generally work faster and smarter than new or first-time indexers and can more easily deal with complicated and challenging texts. They may also have specific subject specialties that allow them to more quickly understand texts in those areas.

Family members, graduate students, and authors themselves rarely have experience in the two basic skills that all professional indexers use: concept identification and term selection. This means that professional indexers can more readily separate out passing mentions and other nonindexable material from relevant concepts that should be captured in an index. Professional indexers also have experience creating appropriate wordings for headings and subheadings to capture the concepts of the text. Writing in the clear, concise, and unambiguous manner necessary for an index is not a skill acquired overnight.

Although some say that authors are the best indexers of their material, this is generally not the case. In addition to not having indexing skills in their writing repertoire, authors often lack the objectivity necessary to properly consider and index their text in a manner most useful to the reader. Authors (and, indeed, most new indexers) tend to over-index a text, including items that do not contain substantive information, thus cluttering the index with irrelevant entries.

Chapter 3 discussed the characteristics of a good index. Professional indexers are used to thinking about those characteristics continually and can generally be counted on to produce indexes that reflect best practices in indexing techniques.

FINDING AN INDEXER

There are several resources available to help editors find indexers. Most publishers have resumes on file or databases of trusted freelancers developed over time. Editors may also rely on word-of-mouth referrals from other editors, authors, or packagers. Additional resources include the American Society of Indexers (ASI), which offers the online Indexer Locator and Jobs Hotline; publishing industry directories such as Literary Market Place (LMP), which lists dozens of indexers (refer to LMP’s Editorial Services Activity Index); and Internet searches. Additional detail on some of these methods and resources follows.

Personal Referrals

Personal referrals are a good guide to finding competent indexers. Other editors or authors can suggest indexers they have worked with successfully. When seeking personal referrals, questions to ask include:

Does the indexer have a subject specialty?
Was the indexer easy to work with? Did the indexer answer emails or phone calls in a timely manner?
Were you pleased with the index submitted? Was it accurate and complete? Were there any problems with file formats or transmissions?
Did the indexer meet the deadline?

Book packagers frequently offer indexing as one of their services. The packager will subcontract the job to an indexer with whom it works on a regular basis. You deal with the packager who basically produces the index for you by doing quality checks and making style decisions.

Books themselves can guide editors to indexers. Look for a book with a great index in the appropriate subject area, and then find out who indexed it by contacting the publisher or author.

Internet Searches

Many indexers have Web sites, and Internet searches may help you find an indexer. Because Internet searches produce so many results, sorting through them will take time.

For example, a Google search on “indexers” produced 354,000 hits. The ASI Web site appeared first. (This excellent resource for finding indexers is discussed in the next section.) The next 60 hits or so also revealed links to Web sites on computer languages, where “indexers” has a different meaning, as well as links to sites of other indexing associations.

A search on “how to find an indexer” (which generated more than 1 million hits) also led to the ASI Web site, as well as to sites regarding a Microsoft Office software utility. In the next 60 hits, we found some valid information on how to locate an indexer, as well as a few links to freelance indexers.

The most links to freelance indexers’ sites were found with a search on “book indexing services.” The top 60 hits or so (of 322,000 hits) were almost all links to freelance indexers’ sites, as well as to information on indexing careers and training.

When indexers are found through online searches, it is advisable to check references and ask to see work samples.

American Society of Indexers

As already mentioned, the ASI Web site tops the list in a couple of sample Internet searches. It provides an excellent resource for information about indexers and indexing.

The ASI home page (www.asindexing.org) offers links to “Advice for Editors and Authors,” which includes information on working with freelance indexers, an indexing evaluation checklist, and reasons to use a professional indexer (“Editors, how much is an index worth to you?”).

The “What Is Indexing” link offers an FAQ on indexing. Although geared for those seeking information on indexing as a career, it also includes information that editors may find useful, such as a review of prices for services and the skills and education that indexers need.

Indexer Locator

The ASI home page also offers a link to “Find an Indexer.” This link provides information on the ASI Indexer Locator and Jobs Hotline.

The Indexer Locator is an online database that lists indexers’ qualifications, including subject specialties. The indexers are ASI members in good standing who have paid to advertise their services. The information provided is self-reported, and ASI makes no representation about the indexers’ qualifications. A perusal shows that many highly qualified and experienced indexers have listings in the Indexer Locator. As of October 2007, 166 ASI members used this vehicle to seek clients.

To use the Indexer Locator, go to ASI’s home page, and then click on “Find an Indexer” either on the left side of the home page or in the main body of the home page. Once on the Indexer Locator page, click on “Search the Indexer Locator Directory.” You may then search by last name, state of residence, subject specialty, language, or type of material to be indexed. Probably the most popular search parameter is subject specialty. Search results give a list of indexer names in random order. That means doing the search again will produce the same names, but the ordering of them will change.

Clicking on any name will direct you to a “Directory Detail,” which provides the indexer’s full contact information, indexing software used, type of materials indexed, subject specialties, and a short description of indexing services and experience. This information will help you find an indexer suited to your project. Do you need a Spanish language indexer? Someone who is willing to take rush projects? Do you need an indexer experienced in FrameMaker embedding techniques?

When you contact an indexer from the Indexer Locator listing, be sure to say you found him through the Index Locator listing. Most likely, you may have to contact several potential candidates before you find one available to take on the project within your schedule and budget.

Jobs Hotline

Another valuable resource from ASI is the Jobs Hotline. This service allows publishers, editors, and authors to announce their need for in-house or freelance indexers. Editors provide job information to ASI, and that information is sent by email to ASI members who have signed up for the Jobs Hotline. Indexers interested in the job respond directly to the editor or author. This service is free to both the client and the ASI member.

From the ASI home page, click on “Find an Indexer.” The Jobs Hotline is a subhead of the Indexer Locator page. Scroll down to the link for Jobs Hotline. Clicking on that link takes you to the Jobs Hotline Submission Form. You’ll find fields on the form for job title, whether the job is on site or freelance, and your contact information. There are also fields to describe the job in detail and specify the type of experience or special knowledge that your job requires.

INDEXER QUALITIES

Once you find a potential indexer, how do you know if she is qualified or will be a good match for your job? Although there is currently no certification of indexers in the U.S., editors seeking professional indexers can inquire about the indexer’s training and look for specific desirable qualities. Checking references is also a good practice when hiring a freelancer for the first time.

Indexers learn how to index in a variety of ways. Many have learned through the USDA Graduate School distance learning courses or other online courses. Some library schools offer indexing courses as part of their curriculum. ASI offers a training program, which will produce many aspiring indexers starting in 2008. Other indexers are self-taught or have learned through on-the-job training. Ask the indexer what kind of training he has had and how many years he has been providing indexing services.

Beyond training and experience, there are several desirable qualities to look for in an indexer. First and foremost, you need an indexer free to schedule the job during your time frame. Some projects will require an immediate time commitment, while others can be planned in advance. Ability to meet deadlines—a crucial quality in indexers—is certainly influenced by availability. Editors may find that their preferred indexer is not available due to previous commitments.

When approaching an indexer with whom you have not worked previously, the indexer’s level of experience can help the editor judge ability to meet deadlines. If an indexer has been in business for a couple of years and has repeat clients, that indexer is no doubt meeting deadlines. Ask the indexer to provide a couple of references to verify timeliness and quality of work.

For novice indexers, contact the indexer’s teacher (if applicable) in addition to checking references. Were lessons completed on time? Did the indexer complete the course? Was course work acceptable?

When seeking an indexer, editors must also determine whether subject matter expertise is required. For some projects, a passing familiarity of the subject will suffice, while other projects may require in-depth knowledge. For some trade how-to’s and lower-division textbooks, subject knowledge may not prove critical. However, most subjects have their own jargon. If the indexer lacks familiarity with a subject, it can lead to poor indexing, such as missing terms of art or picking up unnecessary concepts.

When offering a job to an indexer, editors should discuss the content and level of the text to help determine whether the job is a good match for the indexer (see also Chapter 8). An indexer’s experience with the type of material to be indexed (textbook, monograph, journal, instruction manual, etc.) may also be a selection factor.

Which indexer is hired may also be influenced by budget. If there is little money in the budget for the index, a less experienced indexer may be willing to take the project for a lower rate. Using a less experienced indexer does not necessarily mean a lesser quality index. Everyone has to start somewhere, and sometimes indexers only need an opportunity to prove themselves. The author or editor can help by providing lists of terms to be included in the index. A novice indexer may have more questions or need more guidance, but it could prove to be time well spent if you are helping to develop an indexer who can comply with your style standards and index specifications on future projects.

On the other hand, some projects may merit paying more than the going rate. If you require a very quick turnaround or definite subject matter expertise, you may want to argue for a higher indexing budget. A rush fee may be appropriate to get a quick turnaround, and high-level experience or subject knowledge may require a premium rate of pay. You may also be faced with very large or multi-volume projects requiring more than one indexer or a team approach. This would also call for a larger budget.

CONTRACTS AND LETTERS OF INTENT

Many editors and indexers work under verbal agreements, although ASI recommends written contracts. Written contracts protect both the indexer and the publisher and provide remedies when the terms of the agreement are violated. For example, is a kill fee due to the indexer if the publisher cancels a scheduled project? What if the publisher is unhappy with the indexer’s work? Without a contract, such issues are left to resolution through verbal discussion, which may or may not prove satisfactory. (See Chapter 6 for a discussion of editor/indexer relations.)

A copy of ASI’s Recommended Indexing Agreement is included in Appendix A at the end of this book. An online version is also available at ASI’s Web site. From the home page, click on “Resources” to link to the ASI Sample Indexing Agreement.

An indexing contract should cover at least the following:

Title of the work
Expected page length of the work and description of page layout (type size, number of columns, notes, tables, etc.)
Time schedule and delivery method of final proofs to indexer
Delivery date and method of completed index to publisher
Provisions governing late delivery of material by either publisher or indexer
Provisions for re-indexing or corrections
Specifications for index layout and file submission format
Rate of pay for the index and the payment schedule
Assignment of copyright for the index

See Chapter 8 for additional information on contract negotiations.

PAYMENT

Freelance indexers work hard to meet deadlines, often facing compressed schedules or taking on rush projects. They appreciate prompt payment! A 30-day net is a reasonable payment schedule for both publishers and indexers. Note that indexers’ invoices may specify terms in addition to due dates, such as discounts for early payment or penalties for late payments. Specific terms may be noted on invoices, so be sure to check for those.

Occasionally, book packagers want to wait until they are paid before paying their subcontractors. Unless this was agreed upon beforehand, making indexers wait unreasonable periods to be paid will not create good working relationships. A written contract with specific payment terms will protect both parties.

Chapter 8

What the Editor Needs to Tell the Indexer

Once the editor chooses a shortlist of potential indexers, negotiations can begin. First, the indexer’s availability and suitability need to be determined. Then fees and deadlines need to be set. Additional issues such as schedule changes, editorial changes, and delivery methods for pages and completed indexes will need to be discussed. So what exactly does the editor need to tell the indexer?

SCOPE OF WORK

The scope of the work will help determine the indexer’s suitability and availability for the project. The editor should inform the indexer of the subject matter and complexity of the text, the intended audience of the work, and the length of the text. For example, “I have an upper division college textbook on applied linguistics ready for indexing. It has 395 indexable pages, and I need the index in three weeks.” Giving the indexer a word count is usually not helpful, since the length and density of the finished text will depend on the font in which the text is set.

If the work is a subsequent edition, it is helpful if the editor can let the indexer know the length of the original index and whether the publishers liked that index. Providing the old index as a standard word processing file will allow the indexer to read the headings into his indexing software and use those as the basis for creating the new index.

With such specific information, the indexer can determine whether her current work schedule will allow for taking the project and whether she is qualified or comfortable working in the subject area. Occasionally, indexers may ask to see some sample pages from the project to get an idea of its complexity and density.

The indexer will also need to know how many pages or lines have been allowed for the index. This will determine the depth of indexing required and will help the indexer gauge how much time the project may take. (See Chapter 5 for an in-depth discussion on appropriate index length.) Do not assume that a shorter index will be easier to prepare. It can take a great deal of time to create an index for a limited space, since the indexer must make careful decisions about what to include in the index.

In addition, the indexer will need to know if multiple indexes are required (separate author or plant name indexes, for example) or whether the job requires embedding index terms, adding type codes, or doing any other additional work.

STYLE GUIDELINES

If the index has to follow a specific format, the editor should send the indexer a style sheet or another index done in the desired style. A clear understanding of style requirements will avoid delays and extra work at the end of the project. For information on style and formatting, see Chapter 4, which covers those issues in complete detail.

NEGOTIATING THE FEE

The scope of the work directly affects the fee for the index. Although the editor undoubtedly has a budget for the index, the scope of the work must be considered. For example, a technical medical text with eight index entries per page will command a much higher rate of pay than a how-to on flower arranging with only a few index entries per page.

Indexers need to charge more for preparation of multiple indexes or for embedded indexes, due to the extra time involved in such projects. An experienced indexer can be a good resource in helping the editor or author reach a reasonable fee.

Key elements in fee negotiation are good communication and clearly understood agreements.

Fee Arrangements

Indexers typically charge for their work in one of four ways: per page, per entry, per hour, or per project.

Per-Page Rates

The majority of indexers charge by the page. Again, scope of work will influence the per-page rate. The density and complexity of the text, indexability of figures or illustrations, and number of indexes required all affect the rate. The indexer’s experience level will also be a factor, as seasoned indexers expect to be compensated appropriately for their level of skill and knowledge.

According to the American Society of Indexer’s (ASI) 2004 Salary Survey (most current figures available at press time), median per-page rates were $3.26 to $3.50, with rates ranging from $1.50 to $7.26 per page. Since this survey was conducted several years ago, it is safe to assume that by the time you are reading this, rates will have increased somewhat. New salary surveys, with updated information, will be published on the ASI Web site (www.asindexing.org) as they are completed.

The advantage of this method of payment is that the total fee is determined at the beginning of the project, provided that the editor and indexer agree on what constitutes indexable pages. Front matter and back matter are usually excluded from indexing, although some publishers may request that substantive introductions, glossaries, or appendices be indexed. Editors and authors should advise indexers of their expectations to avoid surprises.

Per-Entry Rates

Another method of charging is per entry. Although much less common than charging by the page, this method is sometimes used for medical and scientific indexes, as well as encyclopedias that generate a large number of index entries per page. It may also be used in periodical or database indexing when a consistent number of entries per publication or issue is generated.

The difficulty in per-entry charges is defining an entry, as definitions vary. Some count each concept as an entry—regardless of heading level—while others count each page reference as an entry. In the following example, the indexer could charge for four entries if concepts are counted; if page references are counted, the number doubles:

Hepatitis

types, 30-32, 41-43

causes, 33-38

risk factors, 44-47, 128

treatments, 100-105, 228-230, 321-323

Editor and indexer must agree on what constitutes an entry, as well as on the average number of entries per page. According to the ASI’s 2004 Salary Survey, median rates per entry were $.70 to $.79, with a range of $.50 to $1.75 per entry. Again, these rates should be adjusted upward by about 15 percent to account for inflation since then.

Per-Hour Rates

Indexers may also charge per hour. Per-hour charges may be appropriate for projects with unknowns. For example, creating a complex embedded index may require much more work than creating a traditional index, so compensation per hour rather than per page would better reflect the amount of work provided by the indexer. Per-hour compensation might also be appropriate for a project in which substantive editorial changes are anticipated, again requiring more work by the indexer.

An experienced indexer will be able to estimate how long a project will take and should provide a range of hours expected for the project. If a limit on the number of hours is required to stay within budget, this limit must be clearly understood by both editor and indexer. In 2004, per-hour rates ranged from $20 to $100, with a median range of $30–$34.

Flat Fee Arrangements

Occasionally, indexers will charge by the project. According to the ASI 2004 Salary Survey, this method is actually more common than charging by the entry, and slightly more common than charging by the hour. Of indexers surveyed, 36 percent charge by the project, while 31 percent charge by the hour, and only 20 percent charge by the entry. Per-project rates could be based on any of the methods discussed: per page, per entry, or per hour. Per-project rates are especially useful when an exact figure for indexing costs is required.

When using any of these fee-setting methods, indexers may ask to see some sample pages from the project to get an idea of its complexity and density. Providing sample pages can greatly facilitate communication and help the indexer to provide a more accurate price for the index.

Special Costs

Editors and authors should be aware that in addition to the fee for the indexing itself, there may also be other fees involved in setting the cost for the index.

Some indexers may charge a cancellation or kill fee if a promised job for which they have allowed time in their schedule is later reassigned to another indexer or never happens at all.

Many indexers will charge a rush fee, which can be a flat fee or a percentage of the original rate, if they agree to take on a job with a greatly shortened turn around time.

While indexers expect to fix errors in the index at no cost, they will ask for special fees for such items as re-indexing due to page changes or inputting author changes to the index.

SETTING DEADLINES

An indexer’s availability will depend on the deadline and amount of time allowed for indexing. Most professional indexers are booked weeks or months ahead, so contracting an indexer early in the production schedule will increase the chances of getting the indexer you want for the job.

Of course, to a large extent, the deadline depends on the production schedule and print date. If the schedule has been slipping all along the way, with the author missing deadlines and the copyeditor running behind schedule, the time available for indexing may be compressed.

How long will it take the indexer to prepare the index? Like many questions about indexing, the answer is: It depends. It depends on the density and complexity of the text, the indexer’s workload, and the publisher’s timely delivery of pages to the indexer. In general, two to four weeks should be allowed in the production schedule for indexing, depending on the length of the text. The following are general guidelines for indexing time, based on the number of pages in the text:

Less than 300 pages: 2 weeks
300 to 500 pages: 3 weeks
500 to 750 pages: 1 month

Even for short works, indexers appreciate ample time, since they usually work on several projects at once. If indexers ask about flexibility in the schedule, they may simply be juggling multiple projects rather than taking more time to index your project. Deadline dates and any schedule flexibility must be clearly understood between editor and indexer. The indexer’s deadline date should also allow the publisher or packager ample time for editing, typesetting, and reviewing the index before it goes to print.

Of course schedules do not always stay on track, and editors may be forced to ask the indexer to meet a nearly impossible schedule. Many indexers are willing to take rush projects, although, as previously noted, some may charge a rush fee. When a schedule is tightly compressed, a higher fee is always a good incentive for an indexer to push to meet the deadline.

According to Hans Wellisch in the second edition of his book, Indexing from A to Z (p. 37), “Most disagreements between indexer and publisher arise on this matter of deadlines, and it is often not easy to arrive at a mutually agreeable compromise.” However, having an established relationship with a professional indexer benefits everyone: The indexer is more willing to accommodate an established client, and the client knows that the indexer will do her best to meet a short deadline.

SCHEDULE CHANGES

When schedules get off track, the editor should advise the indexer as soon as possible. Most indexers are constantly juggling schedules, so knowing that a project has slipped and will not start on the projected date may allow the indexer to take additional work or to start another project sooner.

Because indexers often schedule more than one project at a time, a slipped schedule may affect the indexer’s ability to meet a new deadline. Therefore, it is essential to have some wriggle room in the production schedule if possible. The ASI Recommended Indexing Agreement states, “Should the delivery of page proofs to the Indexer be later than the date(s) specified in Attachment A, the delivery of the index to the Publisher may be delayed by the same number of days.” This assures that the indexer will have ample time to create a quality index.

The same guidelines apply if a project runs ahead of schedule. Although less likely than slipped schedules, this does happen, and the indexer needs to be informed. An editor may send out a project for indexing early, only to learn that the indexer cannot complete it any sooner due to schedule conflicts. Again, good communication is key.

If the production schedule has changed so much that the indexer is no longer available, the editor might ask for a referral to another indexer. Any work already completed by the original indexer should be compensated at the agreed upon rate.

In the rare event that a project is cancelled, the editor should inform the indexer immediately. If there is a written contract or letter of intent between the publisher and indexer, a cancellation fee may be required. The ASI Recommended Indexing Agreement calls for a 15 percent cancellation fee from the party that terminates the contract, as well as a 14-day written notice of cancellation. If working with the indexer under a verbal agreement, a cancellation fee may still be appropriate, especially to pay for work already done.

EDITORIAL CHANGES

Ideally, pages sent to the indexer are in final form with final folios (page numbers). Waiting to send pages to the indexer until the text is in final form with no further pagination changes avoids extra work or delays. Although it may seem practical to have the indexer start writing entries earlier in the production process, it duplicates effort to find those entries later to add page numbers.

The indexer must be notified of any changes in text or page numbers so that corrections can be made. Sometimes the editor or author plans to make the changes after the index is submitted. This approach, however, is not advised. The indexer is the best person to make such changes, since he has software to facilitate a complete and thorough job and at the same time can adjust the index structure and cross-references.

Should substantial editorial changes be required during the indexing process or after the index is completed, additional charges will most likely accrue, as was discussed in the section on fees. Examples of substantial changes that could require re-indexing include:

Changes in page breaks
Rewrites of text or chapters
Reorganization of text or chapters
Changes in figure or illustration placement that cause material to reflow
Changes in page numbers

Some page number changes in the text can be easily fixed in the index. For example, if pages shift but the page breaks are held due to the addition or deletion of text, the indexer can usually correct the index using indexing software.

For example, if a new figure is introduced on page 14, and the original text of that page is bumped to the next page so that the shift involves adding one to each page number (the integrity of the page itself was not disturbed and page breaks are retained), then indexing software has a feature that allows the indexer to add “+1” to each page number starting with the original 14. It is a change done literally in a minute or less. Compare this to an editor making all the required changes manually! Such changes may not add significantly to the cost of the index but may still require a significant review of the index to verify that page references are correct.

Additional types of editorial changes that are easily fixed by the indexer include:

Style and position of see and see also cross-references
Alphabetization order
Subheading order
Page range style
Capitalization
Index style (run-in versus indented)
Punctuation
Index file format, such as supplying an RTF

(Adapted from the ASI Web site, Advice for Editors and Authors)

Trying to make corrections in-house could waste time and result in a poor quality index; an editor could easily miss cross-references and double-postings in the index that are affected by changes in the text. The best practice is to bring any changes required in the index to the attention of the indexer. The indexer can make changes efficiently using indexing software.

Revised Editions

Updated editions of a text require updated indexes. The question is whether to revise the existing index or to re-index the revised text from scratch. There are three main factors that influence this decision: (1) the quality of the original index; (2) the extent of changes in the text; and (3) whether the original index still exists in electronic format and can thus be easily used by the indexer.

Cost-effectiveness must also be considered. Although it may seem an easy task to revise an existing index, this is not always the case. It can actually take as much, if not more, time to revise an index than to write a new one.

Is the original index of poor quality? One assumes that the goal of revising a text is not only to update it, but also to improve it. If the original index is of poor quality, the decision may be made to re-index so as to upgrade the new edition. A poor-quality index cannot be elevated to a high-quality index without significant restructuring and reworking that can take just as long as creating a new index from scratch.

How much has the text changed? If pagination (but not page breaks) has changed due to a few additions or deletions of text, and the previous index is worth using, revision may be appropriate. However, if there are multiple significant text changes that have altered the overall structure of the text or changed its overall argument in an appreciable way, then it should be re-indexed.

Is the old index available in electronic format? If so, is it in a format that the indexer can use? Most indexers use dedicated indexing software to create an index, but indexes are typically sent to the publisher in a word processing format. Conversion services can convert files from word processing formats to dedicated indexing software formats—at a cost. However, if the publisher does not wish to cover conversion cost, the indexer may very well wish to pay for that herself, as she will save considerable time in not having to re-key entries. A simple Internet search for index conversion services will bring up any number of suitable companies offering such services.

Another question to consider is who will be revising the index. Indexing is subjective, and different indexers have different styles and approaches. It may be time consuming for a new indexer to adhere to the approach of the previous indexer and to elegantly integrate newly indexed material into the original index.

In the end, it is the responsibility of the editor or author to determine whether the old index can be repurposed or if a revised index is required.

Embedded Indexing

When index terms are embedded (or tagged) in the actual electronic text files, editorial changes may appear to be less of a problem. For example, if page breaks change, the index term simply shifts to another page along with the text. When the document software produces the index, the term will be assigned a new page number or hyperlink, so the material does not need to be re-indexed.

It appears then that embedded indexing would require fewer index revisions, even if there are editorial changes. If the text is only shifting due to the addition of text or artwork, that may be true. However, real problems can occur when text is rewritten. If an author rewrites or revises text without regard to embedded index entries, codes may be deleted or misplaced in the process.

These problems will not be apparent until a revised index is generated. It is probably safer to re-index a heavily revised book after making sure that all of the original tags are deleted. Trying to compare the old index with the new to identify missing entries and then verifying that the concept is still discussed will be slower than a complete re-indexing.

TEXT DELIVERY

Once the scope of the work is defined and contractual decisions on fees and deadlines have been made, methods and timing of text delivery must be determined.

Delivery Method

How will the text be delivered to the indexer? Traditionally, indexers received page proofs as paper documents delivered via mail or courier. Most publishers use couriers such as UPS or Federal Express, although some may prefer the U.S. Postal Service if time allows. When sending hard-copy page proofs, editors should verify shipping addresses and ask whether to send the package for delivery with no signature required.

Should the publisher want the pages returned after they are indexed or need a hard copy of the index, the editor should provide the indexer with instructions and account numbers for return shipping.

It can be frustrating to both parties to lose time on a project due to failed delivery of pages. Luckily, today, indexers are more likely to receive pages in electronic format. Electronic delivery can save at least two days compared to traditional shipping methods and can allow the indexer to work up to the deadline if necessary. Electronic documents may be sent via email or FTP (file transfer protocol). See Chapter 10 for a complete discussion of electronic files.

Some considerations when sending electronic documents include:

File format (PDF, word processing, etc.)
Attachment size limitations if sending files via email
Software and password requirements for downloading files via FTP

Delivery Timing

The timing of text delivery naturally affects the indexer’s work. The editor should answer two critical questions for the indexer: (1) When will pages be delivered to the indexer, and (2) will all pages be delivered at once?

The projected date for text delivery should be defined in the initial negotiations between editor and indexer. As previously discussed, if this date changes, the indexer must be informed and kept abreast of further scheduling changes. If initial delivery dates are not met, new deadline dates may need to be set.

The indexer also needs to know whether to expect delivery of the entire text on the initial delivery date or whether to expect partial pages delivered throughout the project. If receiving partial pages, the indexer should know in advance (if possible) approximately when to expect each batch, whether batches will be received in page-number order, and whether the bulk of the pages are coming at the end of the project. Part of the initial agreement may be that the indexer will start even if only part of the book is initially in hand.

The projected delivery date for the final batch of pages should also be determined. The indexer’s final deadline may require a specific amount of time between delivery of the final batch of pages to the indexer and delivery of the completed index to the publisher, rather than a specific due date. Even though it may not take long to index a final chapter, the indexer cannot complete a final edit of the index until all pages are indexed. There may also be issues in the index that cannot be resolved until complete pages are in hand.

Hopefully this chapter has provided guidance on some of the important issues that arise as an indexing project is being negotiated. As in any commercial transaction, the editor or author needs to communicate clearly, honestly, and early with the indexer. Professional indexers can readily ask the proper questions and can assist you during the contract agreement process if you are unfamiliar with it.

Chapter 9

Editing an Index Without Tears

The indexer has finished the project and emailed it off to you. It is sitting in your mailbox, blinking balefully at you. You click on the paperclip and open it up. Now what do you do with it? You know you are supposed to “review” it, but how exactly do you do that? It is not like the other sorts of text you regularly handle.

Authors and editors new to indexes may be whizzes at whipping chapter material into shape, but an index is a different sort of beast. Novice reviewers of indexes tend to take one of two very different paths. One choice is not to review it at all, and the other involves a detailed review.

Some authors and editors choose no review: They open up the file, maybe put it into two columns to see what it looks like that way. Perhaps they print it out. Well, it looks like an index. The person who created it has produced a lot of indexes. Yes, that entry seems to pertain to the book. Okay! While many an indexer who is proud of her work would be perfectly happy with that scenario, it’s true that authors and editors can often improve an index with a judicious review.

On the other hand, some clients are determined to review the index thoroughly. So they set about it the same way they would review any text: They read it. They become bogged down in details, mostly to do with the mechanics of the index. Why is that term here when there is something similar over there? Why has the indexer used commas in this case, and semi-colons in that? What is the difference between 99, 100–101 and 99–101?

Things that work perfectly well in the context of the index as a reference document begin to look very strange taken one by one. Much of what the author or editor ends up querying is perfectly normal indexing practice, and they have missed the meat of what they really need to review—whether the index actually helps in finding subject matter in the text.

This chapter aims to assist authors and editors in reviewing an index thoroughly and efficiently, by treating it as what it is: a reference document. Most people (indexers excepted) never read an index from beginning to end. They consult it in order to find things in the text. The most effective way for a non-indexer to review an index is to actually take it out for a test drive. A good index will help you navigate “the road” of the book; a bad one will have you lost by page 3. It should also serve all populations of potential readers.

FROM INDEX TO TEXT: DOES THE INDEX SERVE NEW READERS?

Readers who are new to the text—who have not read it or used it before—need to be served by the index. To check whether the index works for such users, reviewers should think of what a person coming across the book might want to find in it.

Let us say the index under review belongs to a book about whales. What would a potential reader of the book check the index for? Possibly for types of whales, the definition of whales, the Latin term for the species, and perhaps topics such as extinction and endangerment. (This is assuming, of course, that these topics are in the book. Indexers cannot insert information into the book that is not there. Make sure you are checking for things a new user could actually find in the book.)

Can you find the information quickly, either under the term you checked or via a cross-reference? Follow these entries to the pages referenced. Does the material on the pages readily connect to what the index led you to expect there? Check one to three entries per column of index.

If the text is aimed at more than one audience—for instance, for specialists but also for general readers—try to think of dual vocabulary terms you might expect to find. In a book on whales, for instance, a biologist might look up the word “cetaceans” to find information about types and definitions, while an ordinary reader might look under “whales.” If you are finding what you would expect to find this way, the indexer has done a good job. If not, some revision is required.

FROM TEXT TO INDEX: REVIEWING FOR LONG-TERM VALUE

Besides new readers, indexes also have to serve re-readers: those who have kept the book and will consult it in future. These users have a pretty good idea of what is in the text, but they need to be able to find it again.

The reviewer should go over about 10 pages of the text and then try to find subject matter from that section in the index. For instance, if you read a portion of text about the Japanese whaling industry, where would you look in the index when you to wanted to find that information later?

Remember to check in a variety of spots: Under J for Japan is one obvious answer, but there should probably also be an entry or cross-reference under something like “commercial whaling industries.” Try to check not only for obvious, hard-target items like names, but more amorphous subject matter like “folktales about whales and whaling, Japanese.”

Check for relevant entries for at least two 10-page sections for every 100 pages of text. Once again, if you can find what you are looking for either directly or via cross-references, the index is doing its job. If not, you have found a problem.

ERRORS

Much as we would all like to produce perfect work, authors, editors, and indexers all know that this just does not happen. Everyone makes mistakes, and even with the multiple checks and balances that texts being prepared for publication go through, indexers often find a few errors when the text finally gets to them. And that is after the acquisitions editor, the author, the production editor, the copyeditor, the proofreader, and the compositor have all had a go at it.

Indexers generally do their own proofing—some indexers will use a separate proofreader for very large projects, but most of the time there is no budget or schedule to allow for it. So on occasion errors do creep into indexes. Indexers themselves have very low tolerance levels for error. A straw poll of experienced indexers reveal that most expect an error rate of well under 1 percent.

Certainly, publishers with set error rate expectations should be able to hold indexers to that same standard. If an index appears to have a rather high rate of error—more errors than you feel you can easily catch and fix yourself—you should go back to the indexer and ask for additional proofing. Clients should not have to conduct a detailed proofing of the index to ensure its accuracy; that is the indexer’s job.

Of course, that leads to the question of what exactly an index error is, versus a difference of opinion about how to approach a particular entry. Some things—like the proper spelling of a name (Frederick Douglas rather than Frederick Douglass) or a page range of, say, 60–61 for material that is actually covered on pages 135–136—are obvious errors that must be corrected.

However, other issues fall into a less black-and-white category. Part of the problem with delegating to other people is that everyone takes a slightly different approach, and if one does not wish to do everything oneself, one also has to learn to live with that fact. Indexers, who tend to be control freaks, are well aware of this problem and will try to match client expectations.

Clients, for their part, need to be aware that indexers have an enormous amount of experience in terms of where readers look for things, and they usually have very good reasons for the wording and coverage choices they make. Asking about a particular practice, rather than assuming error, is always wise. Things that look odd from the self-conscious point of view of a reviewer may in fact work extremely well when the index is actually being used.

REVISIONS

Doing It Yourself vs. Getting the Indexer to Do It

Most often, the index review yields only a few minor points that authors or editors can easily adjust on their own. In some cases it is not a bad idea to run even minor changes past the indexer, though. First of all, what seems minor to you may in fact have wider repercussions. In an index, a single entry may have many relationships

You may decide to simply change the page range for an entry, for instance. The entry could have variants elsewhere in the index, however (an entry “dogs, 29–30,” may be paralleled with “canines, 29–30,” for instance). Or, say you need to correct the spelling of a name as a main entry; but that name occurs elsewhere in subheads throughout the index, as well.

Again, you may decide to make a minor alteration to the main entry of an array, and that array could be cross-referenced to the original phrase in a number of other places. The indexer is more likely to remember and find all such related entries and will be able to make those changes globally, so the index remains consistent.

In addition, the feedback can be useful. Indexers like feedback, but we do not often get it. We can learn and improve from even minor revision work. This is especially true when it comes to regular clients. Rather than making the same changes over and over again, give them to the indexer so he can learn your style and preferences.

Let’s say the index needs more than a few minor changes. How do you best indicate what you want to ensure you get the best index possible? We should consider index revisions in two lights. First, we will think about the process of communicating changes to the indexer, and then we will consider those things that actually require alteration.

The Revision Process

The biggest problem authors and editors sometimes face in revising an index comes from communication—how best to explain what is not understood or does not work. Five key aspects of the revision process, properly handled, will make communication simpler and clearer.

Ask Questions—Do Not Make Accusations

It is generally a bad idea to begin a note to an indexer (or to anybody, for that matter) with “There is a terrible problem” or “This is a disaster.” For one thing, that automatically sets up an adversarial relationship, which may be very tough to back out of. For another, it simply may not be true.

What might be horrible for an editor to contemplate repairing might be a very simple programmatic fix for an indexer (reformatting all the page ranges, for instance). Or, you may be overanalyzing a basic indexing rule that in fact works perfectly well or can be easily altered. For instance, a co-author of this book once worked with an author who was horribly confused over what appeared to her to be inconsistent ways of treating cross-references, and she spent ages trying to figure out what had happened.

As soon as she mentioned it, however, the indexer could see that what troubled her was a standardized indexing rule about differential treatment of cross-references. The indexer explained the rule she had used and offered some alternatives. The problem was resolved with a few keystrokes.

Group Corrections by Type

Try to group corrective measures by type. Rather than going through the whole index and marking up, say, all the cross-references the way you want them done, give the indexer an example of what they should look like and ask that they all be altered to fit that pattern. This will be much less work for both the reviewer and the person actually inputting any changes. Indexes are generally constructed along rule-based lines, so many revisions fall into patterns.

Give Specific Examples

Vague instructions are not conducive to successful revision. Saying “I just cannot find anything” does not give the indexer much to go on. Try to give a couple of concrete examples of things you could not find and why you expected to find them. If a text on, say, religious belief in eastern Europe contains a whole chapter on folk beliefs and superstitions, and you cannot find any relevant entries, refer the indexer to that chapter and what terms you looked under.

If you find the index does not contain the names of scholars whose work has been cited at length, give the indexer two or three examples of people whose names you expected to find and why. (“I know that we agreed you would not pick up every reference in the book, but I thought you would pick up substantive mentions of scholarly work. For instance, Alexander Fodor’s research is discussed extensively on pages 60–63, and there are specific references to Megan Bang’s field work throughout Chapter 9.”) By giving specific examples, you can allow the indexer to see systemic problems to fix, rather than merely expressing a general dissatisfaction that is hard to ameliorate.

Take Care When Marking Up the File

Many people find it easier to think with a red pencil in hand, literally or metaphorically. Getting into the index file and marking it up is the easiest way for them to see what they want done. However, please do not make half of the corrections in the file directly, and then try to turn the rest over to the indexer.

Novices to index revision sometimes start out by altering the file as they go along, without keeping track of what they have changed, and part of the way through get exhausted by the process and ask the indexer to do the rest. Unfortunately, this can mean that the revisor has wasted a good deal of time and energy, and will probably expend more trying to explain the changes made so far.

Indexers produce a final word processing file for the client, but they do not create the index via that file; they almost invariably use dedicated indexing software, and changes made to the file by the revisor cannot be easily moved from the edited file back into the data, if at all. Plus, if the changes have not been tracked, nothing short of a line-by-line comparison will find them all.

It is much better to provide a list of types of corrections needed, and, if necessary, a properly edited file showing desired alterations to specific entries. Some people still prefer to mark up on paper; indexers can work with that, but remember, you will need to allow time for mailing, and the mark-up will have to be done clearly. A faster option when using paper copy is to fax the material or scan it and attach it to an email.

If possible, use the “track changes” facility that most word-processing systems supply, so that the file can be sent back and forth electronically and is easily readable. That way, even if the revisor’s time and patience does run out and the indexer is asked to correct the index along the lines of what has been done so far, at the least the indexer will have a clear idea of what must be done.

Get on the Phone

Sometimes it is very hard to describe on paper precisely what does not work. Maybe you just need some additional explanation from the indexer for it all to make sense. In that case, do not be afraid to get on the phone. Sometimes talking it over directly will make problems clearer and even make them go away.

Specific Alterations and Corrections

Pinning down the precise problem with an index can be difficult for those unfamiliar with its particular rules and format, quite apart from the issue of communicating that problem to the indexer. The following topics all have a dualistic purpose: They cover the obvious problem that any good editor or writer can see, and they go a little bit deeper, explaining what precise index-specific problems might be causing them.

Spelling Errors

Everyone who writes or edits has noticed this: You do a spellcheck, but on the final reading some horrid error that should have been obvious has somehow been missed. Indexers are just as prone to these occasional spelling goofs as anyone, and the odd spelling mistake should not cause alarm.

An unusual number of such mistakes, however, should trigger some index-specific alarm bells. If the errors are primarily of the sort that should be caught by a good spellcheck program, it may be that the indexer forgot to do a spellcheck. And if the spellcheck was forgotten, what other final checks might the indexer have missed? Suggest to the indexer, “When I spot-checked the index I found five common spelling errors in the first column. That seems like a lot. Would you like to run through your final proofing procedures again?”

You might also want to consider the errors and see if the indexer was perhaps using an American dictionary when an English spelling style was requested or vice-versa. In some international publications the indexer may misinterpret which spelling conventions are required.

Sometimes the spelling errors are not the sort of thing spellcheck would catch—surnames, names of places, unusual terms. Sometimes, on very large projects, editors will have arranged for a special spellcheck dictionary or a file of standardized spellings for words with variants. If such a thing exists, indexers should get a copy, but otherwise they will expect to follow usage in the book.

Nowadays books may be published with multiple spelling conventions, especially if they are multi-authored, and the indexer may choose to use one of those alternative spellings that the reviewer has not thought of. If that is not the case, however, and there are lots of these sorts of spelling errors, it is reasonable for the reviewer to ask the indexer to do another final pass to verify spellings.

Style Issues

The subject matter of the index may be fine, but it may not look the way you think an index should look. Did you give the indexer a style guide or a sample index to follow? Without guidance, indexers have to make their own choices about how to style the index, and there are many perfectly acceptable ways to present index entries. (See Chapter 4 for more on index style and formatting choices.)

Fortunately, most stylistic items are set programmatically, and the indexer should be able to adjust them to the look you want pretty quickly. However, if you did give the indexer some style preferences and they just have not been followed, it may indicate that the indexer has been a bit careless in other matters and that you need to check the index carefully.

Pagination

Pagination seems to be a pretty hard-and-fast topic. Either something is on pages 20–25, or it is not. In fact, that is not quite true. Reasonable people can differ on where exactly they think a topic starts and stops.

Some authors write in very neatly defined chunks that lend themselves to the use of headings, and if a section of text is entitled “Charlemagne’s Benedictine Reforms,” information about how Charlemagne enforced the Benedictine rule in eighth-century monasteries starts where that topic heading starts and ends when it ends.

Other writers, however, are far more discursive and may foreshadow that subject at the end of the previous section, and tie it into the next topic in the following section. Some people want to paginate an entry for such a text strictly by the topic heads, as it gives the user an obvious starting point when moving from index to text. Others believe that it is important to pick up those “fade in” and “fade out” paragraphs, perhaps following on previous or subsequent pages from the specific section in question. Still others make a different judgment call in each case, depending on whether they feel the foreshadowing and tie-in text contain substantive or otherwise unfindable information.

If the indexer’s pagination seems just slightly off to you, this may be one reason why (and nobody’s fault)—you may be thinking about pagination somewhat differently from the indexer. If the entries seem to be consistently one or two pages off, there is the scary but unfortunately not entirely unheard of possibility that the indexer got a version of the text that is not the final pagination (the fault of the person who supplied the text).

If that is the case, the indexer can repaginate the index if provided with the proper pages, but whoever commissioned the index should expect to pay for it. Fortunately, indexing software allows the indexer to sort the index in page order and make the corrections more swiftly than anyone else.

If the pagination appears to be off in an inconsistent way (for example, 16–30 for 160–30; 75 for 76; 8–10 for material on pages 23–24), these are more likely to be mistakes made by the indexer, and the indexer should fix them at no additional charge.

Pagination errors are quite easy to make and not so easy to check, and most indexes probably have a handful. If there seem to be rather a lot of them, however, the reviewer should go back to the indexer, explain how many have been found (give some examples), and ask her to do a page check. Professional indexers can use their software to sort the index in page order and then perform a page-by-page verification of the locators.

Wording of Entries

Authors and editors sometimes have trouble with the wording of index entries. Often this is an issue with only a few entries, easily rewritten. But if this problem pervades an index generally, you will get a better revision of such entries by classifying the problems. Ask yourself a few key questions.

Are the entries too long and involved? For example, let us say an index on foreign policy and religious belief in the early 20th century has the recurring subhead of “Christian anti-internationalism directed against liberalism, modernist theology, and League of Nations by.” In the context of this book, however, the definition of Christian anti-internationalism includes hostility to the precepts of liberalism and modernist theology, and to the ratification of the League Covenant by the U.S. Senate. “Christian anti-internationalism of” is a lot shorter and just as self-explanatory.

Is there some persistent problem with the grammar of the entries? The index has entries such as:

Lloyd George, David

waterworks

Does this refer to Lloyd George’s personal waterworks? To his views on waterworks as a public utility? A preposition inserted to indicate the relationship between the main entry and the subentry would be helpful here.

Alternatively, you may get a series of entries under a main heading, all beginning with the same preposition. You may feel that it looks odd and is really unnecessary. Remember the indexer may have a good reason for choosing a specific type of phrasing, though, so ask why the entries have been structured that way and whether the rules can be changed.

Are the phrasings awkward? Sometimes, to get the most important word to the initial position, indexers have to resort to some fairly twisted constructions. All indexes have a few of them, but in the end they do serve a noble purpose.

The term of art for the specific legal language used in contracts is “contract language,” for instance, but in a book that is entirely about contracts, users are more likely to go to the more specific term of “language,” so the indexer may reasonably invert the phrase as “language of contracts” (with perhaps a cross-reference at “contract language”).

If there seem to be a number of unnatural phrasings in the book that do not serve a useful purpose, however, you may want to give the indexer a few examples of ones that trouble you and some possible rewordings that retain an important word as the initial term.

Are the entries so short as to be cryptic? A main heading “bulldozers” and a subentry “rocks” are not too problematic. We all know the connection between bulldozers and rocks. A main entry of “bulldozers” and a subentry of “eggs,” however, require some explanation.

Alternatively, you may keep finding entries such as “dogs” in a book on, say, Greek philosophy. Some explanation is required for such an entry to explain how it fits into the index. At the same time, indexes are not there to serve as glossaries. An entry for “aischron and kalon” is perfectly reasonable, providing the book is not aimed at rank beginners, even if the reviewer does not know what it means. This is a key concept in Greek philosophy. “Dogs,” on the other hand, comes out of left field as an entry for such a book without some further explanation (“dogs, aischron as typified by,” for example).

Instead of just telling the indexer that the wording of the entries is a problem, specifying the kinds of problems you see with the wording, and giving specific examples, will clarify things for both the reviewer and the indexer and will result in a better revision.

Adding/Subtracting Types of Entries

Indexers tend to make policy decisions about what kind of thing gets indexed (and what does not). If it is something unusual, they will confer with the author or editor, but much of the indexing process consists of a series of such decisions, and really, that is the indexer’s job.

Nevertheless, indexing clients may find material in an index that they did not expect, and they may not find some things they did expect. In a book on a religious or theological topic, the indexer may decide that the audience will want to check biblical citations, so she will include them, either in a separate collation, as an index array, or individually under the names of individual books of the Bible. The author or indexer, however, might feel this is a bit more than anyone will look up. Should they be removed?

First, ask yourself if there is a space issue with the index. If there is, taking out these citations might quickly save some lines. If not, ask yourself if these entries are doing any harm. If they are not causing a problem, why remove them? Someone may want to look them up. If you are still unsure, ask the indexer why he or she included them. There may be a good reason for keeping them that you have not thought of.

Generally, if you want to remove entries, it is always a good idea to ask the indexer why she created them. Novice reviewers often tend to want to take out multiple points of reference. For instance, indexers producing an entry on “farming” will invariably double-post or cross-reference it at “agriculture.” Some reviewers regard this as redundant. Well, it is. Indexes are by their very nature redundant. They are supposed to provide multiple points of entry to the text.

Remember the first stage of the review process, where you actually looked up things in the index rather than reading it? Well, what if you had looked for information about agriculture and it had only been under farming? You would not care that it was someplace else. You were not going to read the whole index to find what you wanted. What looks redundant to the reviewer is extremely useful to the reader of the book, who dives into the index on a specific information search and leaves the index with just that one kernel of information.

But what if you would like the indexer to add material? For instance, you have written a book on foreign policy from the point of view of Canada. You have included comparisons to other countries, but you cannot find any of them in the index under the country names.

Formulate your query about this clearly, categorizing the omission, and give examples. “I was looking for information about specific countries other than Canada and I could not find it. For example, I compare the Canadian diplomatic core to that of Britain and Germany in Chapter 6, but I cannot find entries for Britain or Germany. How did you handle the country material?”

The indexer may have developed a scheme in which countries are listed as subheads under foreign policy topics but not as main entries—not that you have to stick to that scheme. It would be perfectly reasonable to ask the indexer to add main entries for the countries in this instance. But indexers usually follow a system in what they do, so they often have good reasons for the choices that they make. It is always worth a query.

Cross-Referencing

Indexers routinely run programmatic and editorial checks on the cross-references, so if an entry at “Cyclones” tells you to “See also Hurricanes,” you should be able to go to the H’s and find information under that term.

In the course of reviewing the index, a diligent revisor will always remember to check a handful of cross-references. If you cannot follow them across the index—if you go to “Hurricanes” and find nothing there, for instance—you need to speak to the indexer about it.

Do so by giving the indexer some examples of what you expected versus what you got. In the process of spelling it out, you may find that you just did not do what the cross-reference in fact told you to do. If this appears to be the case, and it is not an isolated instance, try to work out and then explain to the indexer what is tripping you up. It may very likely be a stylistic issue the indexer can easily adjust.

Multiple Points of Entry

We mentioned earlier that one of the main purposes of an index is to provide multiple points of entry to the text. If reviewers have had difficulty finding material, it may be that the indexer needs to add more cross-references and double-postings at alternative terms. Indexers can sometimes follow the text a little too closely and not add enough external terms, especially if a book is intended for multiple audiences.

One co-author of this book once indexed a weighty legal tome that seemed aimed at specialist practitioners. The editor, on reviewing the index, told her that the book was in fact heavily used in prison libraries and as a result required many more general terms than were included (“firings. See termination of employment,” for instance). Once informed about this additional audience, the indexer was able to quickly go through the book and add terms that ordinary people, rather than lawyers, use.

There will be some indexes that are just bad. They cannot be fixed and should be quietly smothered in file thirteen. But that is a rare case. Most indexers with professional experience and training produce wonderful work, and judicious review can almost always make that work a little bit better.

Every year ASI gives the Wilson Award to an exemplary index. The winner gives a speech at the annual conference, and almost all of them have stressed that the care, interest, and thoughtful commentary of an editor or author was one thing that moved the index from good to great.

Index review may seem like a daunting task, but with attention to the proper purpose and function of indexes, the reviewer can make a valuable contribution to the overall usability of any text.

Appendix A:

American Society of
Indexers Recommended
Indexing Agreement

DISCLAIMER

The ASI Recommended Indexing Agreement is intended to be informative and is offered as an example of some of the issues that may be related to the relationship between an indexer and a client. ASI does not warrant, guarantee, or in any other way imply that this Agreement will protect your rights. Laws vary from state to state, and a general Agreement such as this may not be applicable in your state or for your particular situation. We strongly suggest that you consult professional legal counsel to obtain competent advice about any contract you may sign or offer to a client.

INDEXING AGREEMENT

This agreement is made on _____________________, 20___ between _____________________________________ (hereafter, “Indexer”), and:
__________________________________________________________________
__________________________________________________________________
__________________________________________________________________ (hereafter, “Publisher”).

Based upon certain preliminary discussions with the Publisher, the Indexer has agreed to perform certain indexing work as specified in Attachment A. Both parties realize that it is very important that the specifications outlined in Attachment A be agreed upon prior to the commencement of indexing work. The Publisher realizes that changes made to these specifications at a later date may result in increased charges. The Indexer realizes that late delivery of work may result in a monetary penalty.

Assignment of Rights

Upon receipt of full payment for the indexing work, the Indexer agrees to assign the following rights to the Publisher (both parties must initial selections below):

____All rights: All original index works authored by the Indexer as a result of work performed under this Agreement shall be considered a “work made for hire” for the purposes of United States copyright laws and are the sole property of the Publisher. The Indexer assigns all rights to the Publisher, including but not limited to all paper media and electronic media rights.

____All paper media rights: The rights assigned by the Indexer to all original index works authored by the Indexer as a result of work performed under this Agreement shall be limited to the reproduction of the index in paper media form. Paper media form includes, but is not limited to, the right to reprint, the worldwide right to publish in paper form, and subsidiary paper media rights.

____All electronic media rights: The rights assigned by the Indexer to all original index works authored by the Indexer as a result of work performed under this Agreement shall be limited to the reproduction of the index in electronic media form. Electronic media form includes, but is not limited to, the right to reprint on magnetic disk, CD-ROM disc, or to make the index available in an online, electronic environment.

____Other rights: See Attachment A.

____The indexer grants the selected rights above at no additional consideration in the form of a worldwide, perpetual royalty-free license to the Publisher.

____Attachment B describes the fees to be paid by the Publisher for copyright assignments.

Author Credit and Editorial Approval

____The Publisher agrees to provide credit to the Indexer either on the copyright page or on the first page of the index itself.

____The Publisher will not provide credit to the author of the index.

____The Indexer agrees to review any editorial changes made to the index and will be available for review of index page proofs during the time period outlined in Attachment C.

____The Publisher agrees to inform the Indexer of any and all changes made to any index authored by the Indexer as a result of work performed under this Agreement. The Publisher also agrees to provide the Indexer with page proofs of the index for the purpose of review by the Indexer.

____Should differences result regarding editorial changes made to the index, the Publisher agrees to remove credit for the index if so requested by the Indexer.

Subcontracting

____The Indexer may subcontract work performed under this Agreement under the following conditions: 1) the Indexer secures copyright to the work performed so that the Indexer is in a position to assign rights to the Publisher; and 2) the Indexer, not the Publisher, is responsible for any and all payments to the Indexer’s subcontractors.

____The Indexer may not subcontract work performed under this Agreement.

Payment

The Indexer shall invoice the Publisher for actual work performed at a rate set forth in Attachment A. The Publisher shall pay said invoices within ____________ days of actual receipt.

Delivery of Work

Both parties have obligations in regard to the delivery of work. Should the delivery of page proofs to the Indexer be later than the date(s) specified in Attachment A, the delivery of the index to the Publisher may be delayed by the same number of days. Should the Indexer not deliver the work by the date specified in Attachment A, it is the Indexer’s responsibility to inform the Publisher of late delivery. At its option, the Publisher may deduct 5% from the payment due to the Indexer for each business day that delivery of the index is delayed. If the delivery of page proofs to the indexer is delayed by five (5) or more business days, the indexer may terminate this contract without prejudice.

Relationship of Parties

Nothing in this Agreement shall in any way be construed to constitute the Indexer as the agent, employee, or representative of the Publisher; the Indexer shall perform its obligations as an independent contractor.

Term

The Indexer will begin work on the date of delivery of initial set of page proofs as indicated in Attachment A and, unless terminated sooner, the Agreement will end when the Indexer’s services are completed.

Assignment

Neither party may assign or delegate its rights or obligations under this Agreement without the other’s written consent.

Termination

Either party may terminate this Agreement by providing notice in writing to the other party no less than fourteen (14) days prior to the commencement of work. The notice of termination shall be effective upon receipt. Should the Publisher terminate this Agreement less than fourteen (14) days prior to the commencement of work as specified on Attachment A, the Indexer shall be entitled upon written request to a 15% cancellation fee based upon the maximum expected payment for work as specified in Attachment A. Should the Indexer terminate this Agreement less than fourteen (14) days prior to the commencement of work as specified on Attachment A, the Publisher shall be entitled upon written request to a 15% cancellation fee based upon the maximum expected payment for work as specified in Attachment A.

Governing Law; Severability

_________________ (state) law shall govern and enforce this Agreement. Any litigation or arbitration between the parties shall take place in ___________________________ County, __________________ (state). If any provision of this Agreement is found by a court of competent jurisdiction to be unenforceable for any reason, the remainder of the Agreement shall continue in full force and effect.

Modification

Any modification, waiver, or amendment of any provision of this contract shall be effective only if in writing and signed by both parties.

This Agreement supersedes all other agreements, whether written or oral, between the parties hereto relating to the subject matter hereof.

The parties indicated below declare that they have read, that they understand, and that they agree to abide by the terms of this agreement. This agreement has been signed by the parties in two identical copies of which each party has taken one.

INDEXER | PUBLISHER
_________________________ | _________________________
Authorized Signature | Authorized Signature
Name: _____________________ | Name: _____________________
Title:______________________ | Title:______________________
Date:______________________ | Date:______________________